<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the christian sabbath Wherein the sanctifying of the Lords-day, is proued to bee agreeable of God, and to the Gospell of Iesus Christ. By Robert Cleaver.</title>
            <author>Cleaver, Robert, 1561 or 2-ca. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5379</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115588</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850806</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850806</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18961)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1512:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the christian sabbath Wherein the sanctifying of the Lords-day, is proued to bee agreeable of God, and to the Gospell of Iesus Christ. By Robert Cleaver.</title>
                  <author>Cleaver, Robert, 1561 or 2-ca. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. M[athewes] and I. N[orton] for Robert Milbourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the great south dore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The morality of the lavv.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16033:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16033:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION of the Chriſtian SABBATH. <hi>Wherein the ſanctifying of</hi> the LORDS-DAY, is proued to bee agreeable to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of GOD, and to the Goſpell of IESVS CHRIST. <hi>By</hi> ROBERT CLEAVER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> and <hi>I. N.</hi> for <hi>Robert Milbourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the great South Dore of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16033:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16033:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN CREVV, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. EDVVARD STEPHENS, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Curſon,</hi> Eſquires; together with their <hi>faithfull Yoke-fellowes,</hi> grace, mercy, and peace be multiplyed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed the <hi>Almighty,</hi> by the goodnes of his providence to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne <hi>you</hi> together in one <hi>earthly</hi> family,
<pb facs="tcp:16033:3"/> that by <hi>relation,</hi> and <hi>bond</hi> of <hi>kindred,</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity,</hi> you ſhould all cal the ſame man, your <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> and according to the riches of his grace, to vnite <hi>you</hi> together in one heauenly family that by vertue of <hi>Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> you ſhould all call the ſame <hi>God,</hi> your <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and ſo more truely become <hi>brethren</hi> or <hi>ſiſters,</hi> each one of you to others in the Lord. For this cauſe, &amp; diuers
<pb facs="tcp:16033:3"/> other reaſons, I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to make choyſe of <hi>you</hi> for my <hi>ſpeciall, &amp; ſelected Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> (ſo farre I preſume of your favour, &amp; kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) and ioyntly to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure you, in <hi>publike,</hi> as <hi>profeſſed friends</hi> to the cauſe wherein I deale, and <hi>Religious obſeruers</hi> of that <hi>ſacred Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for which I con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend: for that, I confeſſe is a great part of my buſineſſe in this briefe diſcourſe enſuing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:16033:4"/> the adverſaries of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> And yet I humbly intreate both <hi>you,</hi> and all other <hi>good Readers,</hi> not to regard the <hi>Sabbath</hi> the leſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is <hi>contention</hi> about it, nor ſuddenly to cenſure the act of <hi>contending,</hi> vntill you be acquainted with the cauſes, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it. There are divers <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> indeed, which in ſhew, &amp; appearance do ſeeme to condemne
<pb facs="tcp:16033:4"/> it, as that to <hi>Timothy. The ſeavant of the Lord muſt not ſtriue, but muſt be gentle toward all men. 2. Tim.</hi> 2. 24. And that to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> I beſeech you brethren, by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that ye al ſpeake one thing, &amp; that there be no diſſenſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10 And <hi>that</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> If it be poſsible, as much as in you is, haue peace With all men,
<pb facs="tcp:16033:5"/> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 18. but none of theſe, nor any other that can be produced, do abſolutely prohibit al maner of <hi>ſtriving.</hi> To <hi>ſtriue</hi> for <hi>error,</hi> and <hi>ſinne</hi> is vnlawfull: to <hi>ſtriue</hi> about things that be <hi>doubtful,</hi> and <hi>vncerten,</hi> is vnlawfull: to <hi>striue</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>curious,</hi> and <hi>needles questions</hi> or matters ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to no edification, or profit, is vnlawfull. And ſo is <hi>ſtriuing</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull when <hi>carnall corruptions, as make-bates</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16033:5"/> be the mouers of it, or ſtirrers in it; as when through <hi>pride,</hi> we ſeeke our owne <hi>vaineglory;</hi> or through malice, and enuy we depraue our brethren. In theſe, and ſuch like caſes, is <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> forbidden, but not ſimply: for then would not the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 3.</note> haue exhorted the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>with earneſtnes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the faith:</hi> neither<note place="margin">Iſa. 59. 4.</note> would the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſo ſharply haue taxed the people of his
<pb facs="tcp:16033:6"/> time, for <hi>not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> for the truth. <hi>Paul</hi> was a peaceable man, and yet he <hi>ſtroue againſt the falſe Apoſtles and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers:</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> is the perfect <hi>peace-maker,</hi> and author of peace, &amp; yet he mightily oppoſed the rabble of <hi>Scribes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſees.</hi> And now to pleade for <hi>my ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>my brethren,</hi> which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by writinge, or preaching, haue trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the ſame ſubiect, have as I done, we are
<pb facs="tcp:16033:6"/> not meere voluntaries in this controverſie, but neceſſarily vrged thereto, as preſted ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: we begin not the quarrell, as Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailants, but onely iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the truth of our doctrine, and cauſe, as Defendants; <hi>our Bookes,</hi> and <hi>Sermons,</hi> being particularly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned, although (I truſt) more <hi>ſound,</hi> &amp; <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe,</hi> then can be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>futed. We are far from <hi>Innovations,</hi> &amp; <hi>Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16033:7"/> in our poſitions, and tenents: we wiſh all good to our <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites,</hi> with a deſire, rather to informe them, by arguments and reaſons, then to diſgrace, or provoke them, by taunts or invectives. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of <hi>your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, loues,</hi> and <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſpoſitions</hi> aſſure mee, that <hi>you</hi> will be eaſily perſwaded of the veritie of <hi>mine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie,</hi> and therefore I
<pb facs="tcp:16033:7"/> ſhall not neede with multiplicity of words, to enlarge it, neither doe I thinke it decent to taske <hi>you</hi> with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of other imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent matters, which neither neceſsitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, nor conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie approoueth of; eſpecially, ſeeing there is as little <hi>Decorum</hi> kept in prefixinge a <hi>long Preface</hi> before <hi>a ſhort Treatiſe,</hi> as in making a <hi>wide dore</hi> for a <hi>narrow building.</hi> And
<pb facs="tcp:16033:8"/> therefore to ſpare both <hi>you,</hi> and my ſelfe from further labour, I briefly conclude, and with due reſpect, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend you to the protection, grace, gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and bleſsing of the moſt High, and remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips for all Chriſtian ſervices. Robert Cleaver.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:16033:8"/>
            <head>A Table of moſt of the principall matters contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this inſuing Treatiſe</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is dangerous to queſtion the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Gods lawes. pag. 1. 2. How the Law retaineth it's <hi>authority</hi> and yet Gods people freede from it. 24.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>The Ceremoniall Law, not ſo much dignified as the <hi>Morall.</hi> 32.</item>
               <item>The Ceremoniall Law, by rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in ſome reſpects was
<pb facs="tcp:16033:9"/> contained vnder the Morall. 35. 36.</item>
               <item>Significant Ceremonies alter not the nature of vnchangeable precepts. 44.</item>
               <item>The moral Law not made <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall</hi> by ſignifications. 33.</item>
               <item>We are not tied to the Jewes ſeuenth day by the fourth <hi>Commandement.</hi> 99.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Moral</hi> Commandements perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. 4. 5.</item>
               <item>The fourth <hi>Commandement</hi> is Moral. 50.</item>
               <item>The Moral Law not made <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall</hi> by ſignifications. 33.</item>
               <item>Nothing is aſcribed to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the word but that which is in a ſpeciall maner to be ſacred and holy 103. 104</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>THe Dignity of the Law in regard of Continuance. 30.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16033:9"/>
               <item>In what ſence a <hi>day</hi> is ſaid to be the <hi>Lords-day.</hi> 104.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>AL Solemne Feaſtes in the law, did by relation, and in ſome reſpects, iſſue from the ſame fountaine that the <hi>ſeuenth-day</hi> did 93</item>
               <item>Whether faith be commanded in the Law? and how. 42</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>THe Law aboliſhed to the Godly, onely in reſpect of the rigorous ſeverity thereof 22.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>Men are made able by grace to do that which is termed Keeping the law. 40</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:16033:10"/>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>THe Law hath a place in mans heart by nature. 11</item>
               <item>The writing of the law in mans heart by nature, being blotted and defaced by his fall; is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the regenerat. 12 13.</item>
               <item>By Law is ſometimes, ment the irritation and provocation to ſinne which it accidentally occaſioneth (but cauſeth not) in the vnregenerate. 18. 19.</item>
               <item>The Law belongeth to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. 27.</item>
               <item>There is no alteration or change of nature in the <hi>duties</hi> of the Law. 29</item>
               <item>Five Arguments proouing the Morality of the Lords day. 52 to 65</item>
               <item>Five Obiections againſt the Morality of the Lords-day anſwered 66 to 89.</item>
               <item>The Lords-day proved to be of divine inſtitution. 103 &amp; ſeq.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16033:10"/>
               <item>The Lords-day is immutable. 111.</item>
               <item>The firſt day of the weeke, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be the Lords-day that is to be obſerved. 114</item>
               <item>Becauſe a Chriſtian ſhould be every Day holy; it will not follow, that the Lords-day is not to be obſerved. 119 &amp; ſeqq</item>
               <item>Chriſtians in the Primitiue Church chooſing the firſt day of the weeke, for the Lords-day; doth not proue that it is not of diuine Inſtitution. 137. 138. &amp; ſeqq.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>THe <hi>Morality</hi> of <hi>the Lords-day, proved by Teſtimonies of the</hi> ancient fathers. 131. &amp; ſeqq.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Morality</hi> of <hi>the Lords-day, proued by Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the</hi> worthy Moderne writers. 106. &amp; ſeqq</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16033:11"/>
               <item>The Morality of the Lords-day proved by the doctrine of the Church of England. 140. 141. &amp; ſcqq.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>OBiections pretended out of the Fathers againſt the morality of the Lords-day anſwered. 129 &amp; ſcqq.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>SCriptures anſwered and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red which the Adverſares produce to proue that the Law is aboliſhed. 15. 16. &amp; ſeqq.</item>
               <item>Mutation of <hi>ſervices</hi> alter not the nature of the law. 47.</item>
               <item>There greeuous <hi>ſinne</hi> that ſhal enterprize to alter the Lords-day. 112.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:16033:11"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ALl the Morall Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements are perpetuall. <hi>Cap. 1. Pag. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>No ſignifications, expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or change of duties and ſeruices, haue made any of the Morall Commandements, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall. <hi>Cap. 2. Pag. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fourth Commandement is a Morall Precept. <hi>Cap. 3. pag. 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All conſecrated time, is the obſeruation of the Fourth. Commandement. <hi>Cap. 4. Pag. 90.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16033:12"/>
               <item>The LORDS-Day is a conſecrated time, and of diuine Inſtitution, and immutable. <hi>Cap. 5. Pag. 102.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16033:12"/>
            <head>THE MORALITY OF THE LAVV.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> All the Morall Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements are perpetuall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing<note place="margin">It is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to make que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the authority of Gods Lawes.</note> ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, as that Sathan will not impute vnto it defect and want; nor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16033:13"/> any thing ſo cleare and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, as that by infidelity and carnal reaſon it cannot be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into queſtion, &amp; made lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto doubts: otherwiſe no mortall creature would haue attempted to impeach the ſacred authority of Gods owne moſt holy Lawes, which haue reteined their force, and exerciſed their power ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand yeares, as haue beene ſince the beginning of the World. If the exquiſite righteouſneſſe of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declared, were ſubiect to diminution, as that it might bee worne out by time; or if his Soueraignty were termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and to continue but for a certaine number of yeares; or if the loue thereby requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of men towards their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, or of each one to another were now become needleſſe, &amp; of no neceſsity, they would
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16033:13"/> be the more excuſable, who ſeeke the ſubuerſion of theſe heauenly Statutes: otherwiſe, they commit ſpirituall treaſon againſt the <hi>Diuine Maieſtie.</hi> It is not ſafe to depraue the Acts, which hee hath done, and to debaſe the workes of his hands; much leſſe will hee put vp the reproach of that which by his <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> hee ſpeaketh, and the indignity offered to the gracious word; of his mouth; hee cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the glory of his Lawes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> of his Statutes, of his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Oracles to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced. Let no man thinke, that wee begin our Diſcourſe with Fictions, by faining of faulty and erroneous perſons, who, with little difficulty, may bee refuted: wee fight not with our owne ſhadow, wee complaine not without grieuance, and iuſt cauſe of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16033:14"/> griefe: For, there are reall Aduerſaries, and not imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, lately riſen vp, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce both the <hi>Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> and all other the Scriptures of the Old <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as abrogated and aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Leuiticall <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It will not then be ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, (as a worke vndertaken without due cauſe, or hope of good effect) as briefly as may be, to make it appeare, that neither the <hi>Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> nor any parts of the <hi>Morall Doctrine</hi> of GODS moſt holy <hi>Word,</hi> in force be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comming of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are antiquated, &amp; made force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, by his birth, preaching, practiſe, death, reſurrection, or aſcention.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, himſelfe expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth any ſuch meaning, or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16033:14"/> intent, on his part: for it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that ſome licenciouſly hoped for ſuch a carnall liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſome maliciouſly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brayded him with purpoſe of ſuch an impious innouation: and therfore, that none might take occaſion to conceiue any ſuch thoughts of him, hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly maketh his mind known<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 17.</note> to the contrary. * <hi>Thinke not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that I am come to deſtroy the Law or the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: I am not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, but to fulfill them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 Secondly, the Apoſtles, and Writers of the Bookes of the New <hi>Teſtament,</hi> doe often produce them as authenticke witneſſes of GODS <hi>ſolide Truth,</hi> and <hi>the Sacred Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of his holy Spirit:</hi> yea, and haue founded thereon maine ſubſtantiall Points of Faith: which they would not haue done, if ſuch Books
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16033:15"/> and ſayings had then ſtood cancelled, or beene growne out of date.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection.</head>
                  <p>But they hope to auoid this by interpreting themſelues, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding their owne meaning; <hi>which is,</hi> That they deny not any Commandement, or words, or ſentences of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cited in the new, to bee the Scripture: For ſo much as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated by the Euangeliſts, or in the writings of the Apoſtles, they acknowledge to be GODS owne words: But no more then are there expresſly ſpecified: and not them to be ſuch now, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that voyce, which GOD vttered once in Mount Sinai; or of that hand, which wrote them in the Tables; or of that ſpirit, whereby Moſes recorded them in <hi>Exodus,</hi> or <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> or other places; or, whereby the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16033:15"/> Prophets either ſpake or writ: But by vertue of an Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Spirit, whereby they are tranſlated into the Goſpell, and become meerely Euangelicall.</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>This they ſay, and if it proue true in the particulars, they ſay well: Otherwiſe we muſt thinke, they care not what they ſay, ſo that they may die their foule cauſe with a faire colour. Let the point therefore come to ſcanning. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 2. 10. 11.</note> 
                        <hi>Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet faile in one point, hee is guilty of all; for hee, that ſaid, Thou ſhalt not commit Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſaid alſo, Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Three things are heere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirable, and duely to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of: One, what this Law
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16033:16"/> is: The next, who bee Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents in the tranſgreſsion thereof: The third, who is the Author that giueth autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity vnto it.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Touching the Firſt: The Law muſt needs bee the <hi>Ten Commandements,</hi> as the inſtances in the <hi>Seuenth</hi> and <hi>Sixth,</hi> being parts of the whole, doe teſtifie: And to theſe, wee ſee, hee yeeldeth both the ancient title, and power; they are authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Edicts, and require an intire obedience. Take them as repealed in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and reuined in the new, and you cannot call them the whole Law: For all of them are not there in expreſſe termes, and particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded: neither will our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites grant that the <hi>Fourth Commandement</hi> hath any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation therein, although it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16033:16"/> bee indeed by Chriſt ratified with the reſt: but yet onely in generall words, and by firme conſequents.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Concerning the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; they are all cruell men,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> and vnchaſt perſons, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, in any place of the World, which giueth himſelfe ouer to any iniquity, and theſe are obnoxious, that is, guilty of tranſgreſsion, &amp; ſubiect to that penalty which the Law doth denounce. Now in <hi>Iames</hi> his time, the Goſpell was not ſo vniuerſally ſpread, as that all men euery where ſhould either yeeld obedience to it, or be conuicted of the violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. For the laſt, who it was that ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultery; Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> It muſt needs bee hee, that ſaid (<hi>I am the Lord thy God that brought thee out of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16033:17"/> Land of Egypt, &amp;c,</hi>) and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered all the other Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements to his people in the Wilderneſſe: For hee is that * <hi>One Law giuer, which is able to ſaue and to deſtroy. Cap.</hi> 4 12.</p>
                     <p>One other place alſo ſhall bee produced, to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> in their Allegations of Texts out of the Law, and other parts of the Old Teſtament, reſpected the authority of thoſe Scriptures, out of which they haue deduced them; and that is the <hi>Sixth</hi> to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, verſe</hi> 1. where he giueth this exhortation: <note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 6. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>Children obey your Parents in the Lord.</hi> Secondly, hee yeeldeth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof, <hi>for this is right:</hi> Thirdly, hee confirmeth the ſame by the words of the <hi>Fifth Commandement; Honour thy Father and thy Mother.</hi> Fourthly, hee amplifieth that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16033:17"/> Precept, and ſheweth two cauſes why it ought very much to bee regarded: One is from the ſite and place, which it hath in the <hi>Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue:</hi> It is the <hi>firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> namely, of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and that which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth before all the reſt in the Second Table. The other is from a forcible Adiunct: It hath a <hi>Promiſe</hi> annexed vnto it, which is peculiar to it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, in that Table. Now why ſhould the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> vrge theſe Arguments ſo earneſtly, if that Scripture had loſt all its wonted vertue.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, no temporary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,<note place="margin">3. The Law hath a place in Mans heart by nature.</note> nor that which was expirable, can bee found to haue by nature a place in mans heart, or a continuance therin by grace, after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience &amp; practiſe of it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolu'd in the Church. But theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16033:18"/> Commandements were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Adams</hi> heart, at his creation: (otherwiſe he had not beene faſhioned, after the image of GOD) and after his fall, both himſelfe and all his poſterity ſhew the effect of<note place="margin">Rom. 2. 19.</note> the Law written in their hearts: <hi>Their conſcience bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring witneſſe thereunto,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teſtifieth. The vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, the vnbeleeuers, the very Heathen, by light of reaſon and naturall conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, can diſcerne of equity, and iniquity; of honeſty, and diſhoneſty; of laudable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and damnable crimes; as what reward liberall &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull men deſerue, and how ſeuerely Atheiſts, Murderers, Adulterers, &amp; ſuch like male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, ought to be puniſhed.</p>
                     <p>But theſe goodly Writings being blotted, and much defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, in our firſt Parents, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16033:18"/> their poſterity, by ſinne, and corruption, they are copied out faire in the regenerate, by the Spirit of grace, through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Dauid,</hi> made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to his Image, and a figure of him, profeſſeth of<note place="margin">Pſal. 40. 8.</note> himſelfe, ſaying; <hi>I deſired to doe thy will, O my GOD: yea, thy Law is within my heart.</hi> Which, in like manner hee teſtifieth of all other, that bee truly godly, with a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the bleſſed effects thereof; when he thus deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth<note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 30. 31.</note> them. <hi>The mouth of the righteous will ſpeak of wiſdome, and his tongue will talke of iudgement: For the Law of GOD is in his heart, and his ſteps ſhall not ſlide.</hi> Thus GOD wrought in his people, in thoſe former ages, before Chriſt, and promiſed a continuance of the ſame grace, with a large addition thereto, in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16033:19"/> time of the Goſpell; as the<note place="margin">Heb. 8. 10.</note> Apoſtle to the Hebrewes proueth out of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<note place="margin">Ier. 31. 31.</note> of <hi>Jeremy. This is the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, that I will make with the houſe of Iſraell; after thoſe dayes, ſaith the LORD, I will put my lawes in their mind; and in their heart I will write them, &amp; I wil be their GOD, &amp; they ſhall be my people.</hi> He. 8. 10.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, if the authority of the Law, and all the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament had beene aboliſhed by the death and reſurrection of Chriſt, and none elſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in force, but only thoſe particular words, and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which are repeated in the new: It muſt needs follow that all the time betweene his reſurrection, and the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the New Teſtament, (which was of diuers yeares continuance) men lined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diuine Law, or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16033:19"/> the former were all void, and no mans conſcience ſubiect vnto them: and none other as then enacted, &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in their places.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>Now we are to inquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the grounds of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, that it may be ſeene by tryall. What validity, for their purpoſe, may bee found in their allegations.</p>
                  <p>Their Firſt place is out of<note place="margin">Scriptures cleared, which the Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to proue the Law abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</note> 
                     <hi>Luke 16. 16. The Law and the Prophets were vntill Iohn: ſince that time the Kingdome of GOD is preached, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one preſſeth into it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their Second, is out of the ſeuenth to the <hi>Romans, ver. 6. Now we are deliuered from the Law, being dead vnto it, wherein wee were holden; that wee ſhould ſerue in newneſſe of Spirit, and not in the oldneſſe of the letter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their Third is out of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16033:20"/> third Chapter of the ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians, verſ. 11. If that which ſhould be aboliſhed was glorious, much more ſhall that which remaineth bee glorious.</hi> To euery one of theſe an Anſwer ſhall be made in order.</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwere to the firſt place.</head>
                     <p>The meaning of Chriſt, in<note place="margin">2 Luke 16. 16. proveth not Chriſts abrogating of the Law or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</note> that of <hi>Luke</hi> is, that the Law and the Prophets vntill <hi>Iohn</hi> his time, continued their prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, adumbrations, and ſignifications of the future happy eſtate of the Church which now by his Miniſtery was declared to bee at hand; for that hee was the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate foregoer of Chriſt his owne perſon, and the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſent to proclaime his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, who was now in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16033:20"/> to publiſh his owne Goſpell, &amp; to enter vpon the worke of Mans redemption. This interpretation is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by that, which in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 11. 13. is deliuered: <hi>All the Prophets, and the Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied vntill Iohn.</hi> But what is heere for excluſion or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, either of the Law or the Prophets? not ſo much as the <hi>Leuiticall rites or ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> were then abrogated: for ſo ſhould they be aboliſhed by <hi>Iohn</hi> his comming, rather then by Chriſt his reſurrection; yea and that before they were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, or that which was ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified by them, accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer to the ſecond place.</head>
                     <p>Now come we to that, in the <hi>Seventh</hi> to the <hi>Romans, Now we are delivered from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16033:21"/> Law: &amp;c.</hi> It is apparent by the purpoſe, and all the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of that Chapter, that by [<hi>Law</hi>] is vnderſtood that irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to evil, and provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſin, which the Law of GOD accidentally occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth, (but properly doth not cauſe,) in vnregenerate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The vicious diſpoſition, and corruption, which is in men, before Grace; that fleſh which is naturally in all the Sonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> reſtraineth them with the greater irkſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, from the performance of ought, that is required, (eſpecially to doe it well, and in a due manner,) and inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them with a more greedy appetite (as I may ſo call it) to effect, thinke, ſpeake, and doe thoſe things, which by the Lord are prohibited. It is like to a ſwift and violent ſtreame of water, which will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16033:21"/> endure no reſiſtance, but beareth downe Dammes and flood-yates, &amp; all other ſtops, that ſtand in the way, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his paſſage. This is the <hi>Law,</hi> and this is the <hi>Husband,</hi> ſpoken of in the beginning of the Chapter; and every man is a Wife ſubiect to the ſame, ſo long as he remaineth meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carnall, and ſuch a one, as he was by generation: But, when he by Grace and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is once truly morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, this party is dead, and ſo is that <hi>Husband,</hi> reigning ſin; the bond of marriage is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and the ſame perſon vnited vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by his Spirit, and ſo obtaineth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from the <hi>Law,</hi> which in this place is ſpoken of; and that indeed, is a reſtitution to the true vſe of the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> rather then a divorce, or ſeparation from it.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16033:22"/>
                     <p>This expoſition is not of<note place="margin">Maſter <hi>Beza.</hi>
                        </note> our owne coyning; it hath not onely the conſent of moſt iudicious interpreters but a ſound confirmation from the premiſſes, and ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of this Text here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by our oppoſits; as<note place="margin">Ver. 5.</note> thus. <hi>When we were in the fleſh, the motions of ſinne, which were by the Law, had force in our members, to bring forth fruite vnto death. Sinne tooke an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note> 
                        <hi>by the commandement, and wrought in mee all maner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence: for without the Law ſinne is dead. Sinne tooke an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 11.</note> 
                        <hi>by the commandement, &amp; deceiued me, and thereby ſlew me. Wherefore the Law is holy, and the commandement is</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 12.</note> 
                        <hi>holy, and iuſt, and good. Now</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> 
                        <hi>is that, which is good, made death to me? God forbid! But ſinne, that it might appeare ſin, wrought death in me, by that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16033:22"/> which is good: that ſinne might bee out of meaſure ſinfull, by the commandement.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The venemous operation of carnall corruption, and how miſcheevouſly, by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Gods <hi>Law,</hi> it inciteth vnſanctified men to rebellion, may evidently be diſcerned in every one of theſe ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And that it is called by the name of a <hi>Law</hi> is plaine in theſe words. <hi>I ſee another</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 23.</note> 
                        <hi>Law in my members rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of my minde. In</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ver. 25.</note> 
                        <hi>my minde I ſerue the Law of the Lord, and in my fleſh the Law of ſinne.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer to the third Place.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The meaning of that,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 11. Conſidered and cleared</note> in the third to the <hi>Corinths</hi> is to be expended; where it is willingly granted that the <hi>Morall Law</hi> is ſpoken of, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16033:23"/> that, which was to be aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: yet not ſimply, but in ſome reſpect onely: not as it is the rule of Obedience to Gods holy will; not as it giveth directions for the due ordering of every mans wayes; not as it preſcribeth the duties of holineſſe, and righteouſneſſe. But as it is <hi>A Killing letter,</hi> and <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of death, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> formerly mentioned, &amp; as it <hi>concludeth all vnder the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 10.</note> 
                        <hi>Curſe, who continue not in all things, which are written in the booke of the Law, to doe them.</hi> So that the rigorous ſeverity thereof is that onely, whereof <hi>Paul</hi> there ſpeaketh: And nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that alſo, without limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For it is not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that al men promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are exempted from the ſtrict ſentence of it; but thoſe<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 1.</note> alone. <hi>Who are in Chriſt Ieſus,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16033:23"/> which walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit.</hi> The domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion &amp; power of it, ouer-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumatious and wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, was as ample in <hi>Pauls</hi> time and is in theſe dayes, as euer it had bin in <hi>Moſes</hi> his gouernment, and before <hi>Chriſt</hi> his comming.</p>
                     <p>There are beſides theſe Scriptures by our Aduerſaries vrged, ſome other Texts ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to contradict our Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching the perpetuity of the <hi>Morall Law.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is requiſite that, as wel as we can, wee cleare the point, by giuing reſolution to all ſuch doubts, as may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe thereout. One is in the ſixt to the <hi>Romans, ver.</hi> 14.<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 14</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yee are not vnder the Law, but vnder Grace.</hi> Which might
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16033:24"/> giue occaſion of demand, how the <hi>Law</hi> doth retaine its au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and yet the people of God to enioy their immunity from it?</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The purpoſe of the Apoſtle<note place="margin">How Gods law retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and yet Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple freed from it.</note> is to be ſearched out, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, both for the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the words, and alſo for the avoyding the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequence, that otherwiſe would inſue thereupon. His drift therefore is to excite the ſeruants of God manfully to ſtand out againſt ſinne, for the perfecting of their morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. The argument of his Exhortation is, from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted hope of their ſucceſſe and victory. But wherevpon is that grounded? Vpon the happy alteration of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, &amp; condition. Once they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16033:24"/> were vnder the <hi>Law</hi> that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily exacted obedience, and yeelded no aſsiſtance for the performance of it: nay, rather that, which was the <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 56.</note> 
                        <hi>ſtrength of ſinne,</hi> and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred occaſion (although faultleſsly) to corrupt, and victious fleſh, of mutinie, and rebellion againſt Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>But now they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Grace;</hi> that is, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> communicated vnto them; by vertue whereof that which is required of them, they ſhall haue power to doe: and that, which is done by them, (though not exquiſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in full meaſure,) ſhall be accepted, and their ſoules dayly ſtrengthened againſt al the remnants of corruption. It is true therefore that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> are not in <hi>Bondage to the Law, nor vnder it,</hi> as hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the chiefe and principall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16033:25"/> place, ſo as <hi>Grace</hi> could not haue the predominancy; but ioyned with the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and being ſubordinate thereunto; continueth to the end of the world a powerfull, &amp; effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ordinance of the <hi>Almighty.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another</hi> Text, that may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 24. 25 maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the matter in queſtion.</note> matter to an obiector, is in the third to the <hi>Galatians ver. 24. 25. The Law was made our Schoolemaſter to Chriſt, that we might be made righteous by faith.</hi> But, <hi>after that faith is come, we are no longer vnder a Schoole-maſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He</hi> ſpeaketh of that <hi>Legall</hi> adminiſtration, and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which the Lord exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over his people, in the old
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16033:25"/> Teſtament; (both the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, and Morall Law</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iointly in force;) when they were as children at ſchoole, and in their minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and conſequently now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and come to an end the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church being (as it were) men of riper yeares and therefore this concerneth not the matter in queſtion.</p>
                     <p>There is, (by report) an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other<note place="margin">The law belongeth to the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate.</note> erronious opinion now latelyer hatched, of thoſe, which confeſſe that the <hi>Ten Commandements</hi> are not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally abrogated: but yet deny that they belong at all to them, that are in the ſtate of Grace, and converted to the faith: but to thoſe alone which are as yet vnſanctified. The vnſoundneſſe whereof, I hope hath appeared, and beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felled by that, which hath beene hitherto ſpoken. For
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16033:26"/> did (<hi>Paul</hi> perſwade vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving<note place="margin">Eph. 6. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to honour their <hi>Parents,</hi> and apply vnto them the promiſe? Or did <hi>Iames</hi> giue teſtimonie of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane perſons for well doing, in keeping the <hi>Royall Law,</hi> (that is) the <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of God, which are as the Kings high-way, for all degrees to walke in? If they take that to <hi>Timothy</hi> or their<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 9.</note> ground, <hi>The Law is not giuen to a righteous man,</hi> they much miſtake their marke: For there he ſpeaketh of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to bee inflicted, and not of duties to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16033:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> No ſignifications, expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or change of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſeruices have made any of the morall Commandements Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the proofe<note place="margin">No altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or change of nature, of the duties of the law</note> of this point, wee will lay downe a few poſitions, as our ground-worke, ſuch, as I hope, will be found infallible, and vndeniably true preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16033:27"/> alſo, for the manifeſt confirmation of that, which is to be declared.</p>
               <p>The firſt is; That the <hi>Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 The digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the law in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> with the precepts of it, both before <hi>Chriſt</hi> his incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and ſince, hath beene in high honor, and eſtimation (&amp; that by the warrant of the <hi>Holy. Ghoſt</hi>) for the author, equity, and efficacy; as alſo for the antiquity, conſtancy, and continuance of the ſame. They were meant, when <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſaid. <hi>What Nation is there</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo great, who hath God ſo nigh vnto them, as the Lord our God is, in all things, that we call vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for? And what nation is there ſo great, that hath ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and iudgements ſo righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as all this Law, which I ſet before you this day?</hi> And they were included, when <hi>David</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Law of the LORD is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 7.</note>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16033:27"/> 
                  <hi>converting the ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">8.</note>
                  <hi>The teſtimonie of the LORD is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">9.</note>
                  <hi>The ſtatutes of the LORD are right, reioycing the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Commandement of the Lord is pure, inlightning the eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The feare of the Lord is cleane induring for euer, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when he ſaid. <hi>All his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 111. 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Statutes are true; they are ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed for ever, and ever. Pſal.</hi> 111. 7. 8.</p>
               <p>This was the glory, and dignitie, that thoſe Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements had, in antient times whiles the old Teſtament yet continued. Then, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was come, hee both confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and commended them to poſterity; that, yeelding the place of ſuperioritie to the Goſpell, they ſhould (with it, and for it, and by it) retaine their honor, by giving di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16033:28"/> for Chriſtian behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and receiving due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in an holy maner, from the faithfull ſervants of God, in the Church, throughout all ages, whiles the world ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Second Poſition is,</hi> That<note place="margin">2. Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all law not ſo much dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nified as the Morall.</note> the <hi>Ceremoniall Law,</hi> with the <hi>Leviticall</hi> ordinances, have never beene ſo much graced, no not then, when it moſt flouriſhed, &amp; was with great ſolemnity obſerved: for it was alwaies, from the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, to the finall abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment, but a <hi>ſhadow of the bodie to come,</hi> although made<note place="margin">Col. 2. 17.</note> vſefull, by Gods grace, to thoſe, that rightly vſed it. To the <hi>Galaetians</hi> it is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a <hi>Schoole-maſter,</hi> which vſeth, with rod and diſcipline to nurture thoſe, whom hee is ſet ouer. Yea, to a priſon, or houſe of reſtraint, wherein
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16033:28"/> Captiues, or bondmen are wont to be taſked with worke for thereto ſeemeth to be the alluſion, when it is ſaid. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith came, wee were kept</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>vnder the Law, and ſhut vp vnto the faith, that ſhould bee afterward revealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our third Poſition is,</hi> That<note place="margin">3 The Moral law, not made Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial, by ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp;c.</note> in caſe <hi>ſignifications,</hi> and <hi>expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable types</hi> could haue made any <hi>Morall Commandement</hi> to become <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> the whole morall <hi>Law</hi> ſhould have beene much debaſed by a privation of their firſt exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and brought into the condition of theſe Leviticall conſtitutions, as hauing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers precepts of it, once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending vnder them ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſignificant, and rituall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</p>
               <p>This would be the more perſpicuous, and with leſſe difficulty apprehended if it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16033:29"/> were contriued, into an <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheticall,</hi> or <hi>Connexiue Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme,</hi> as.</p>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <label>Propoſition.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>If ever ſignifications, in the ſervices of God, could haue made a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral commandement ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall: then a great part of the perpetuall morall law ſhould haue growne to be Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, and temporary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <label>Aſſumption.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But no part of the morall law is growne to be Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16033:29"/> and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <label>Concluſion.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Therefore, ſignifications, in the ſeruices of God could never make a morall Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ceremoniall and temporary.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Aſſumption</hi> is beyond all exception: For to affirme the ſame thing to be both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, and temporary, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth very neere to a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. And the Sequell of the propoſition is as evident, becauſe the whole ceremonial law was contained vnder the morall; although not direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16033:30"/> and in expreſſe termes, yet with a reference thereunto, and by implication; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſome reſpects, though not in all.</p>
               <p>For, conſider it according to the motiue and occaſion thereof, which was mans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition by his fall, and ſinfulneſſe; and ſo it was accuſatory, and for convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Conſider it according to the end of it, which was to direct men vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in hope of expiation of ſinne, through his blood, and of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying Gods wrath, through his mediation; and ſo it was <hi>Euangelicall.</hi> But conſider it according to the practize in ioyned, as a ſervice to be done to the Lord; and ſo it was a duty of loyalty, and a worke of obedience.</p>
               <p>For, Firſt, the loue of the godly, was much declared in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16033:30"/> the exerciſe of them, as <hi>David</hi> profeſſeth of himſelfe in the<note place="margin">Pſal. 84 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalme,</hi> when he ſaith. <hi>That his Soule longed, yea fainted for the courts of the Lord,</hi> (where his ceremoniall worſhip was ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated) <hi>and there his heart, and fleſh reioyced in the living GOD.</hi> Now whither loue is to be reduced, <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth,<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 8. 9</note> when he ſaith. <hi>That loue is the fulfilling of the Law;</hi> of that <hi>Law,</hi> which ſaith. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery: thou ſhalt not kill; thou ſhalt not ſteale, &amp;c.</hi> So much as any man loueth, ſo neere he approcheth towards the fulfilling of the law, though none but <hi>Chriſt</hi> could euer attaine to the full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The right vſage of them was then, ſome part of the way of righteouſneſſe, and therefore it is ſaid of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that <hi>They</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 6.</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16033:31"/> 
                  <hi>were both iuſt before God, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 1. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>walked in all the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Ordinances of God, without reproofe.</hi> It is agreed vpon, among the Expoſitors, that by <hi>Ordinances</hi> are meant the Ceremonies of the old <hi>Law,</hi> being then in force. And it is manifeſt that Gods will declared in his <hi>Ten Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> hath euer beene the rule of <hi>Righteouſneſſe;</hi> as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> inſtructeth parents to teach their children, ſaying, <hi>This ſhall be our righteouſneſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dent. 6. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>before the Lord our God, if wee take heede to keepe all theſe Commandements, as hee hath commanded vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And let this be added vnto the former reaſons, in the third place, That it was a ſin to neglect, contemne, or abuſe them, as <hi>Eli</hi> his ſonnes did<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 13 14. 15.</note> and cauſed the people to doe alſo. Now it is well knowen,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16033:31"/> and that by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that. <hi>Whoſoeuer ſinneth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>tranſgreſſeth the Law: for ſin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law:</hi> Euen of that <hi>Law,</hi> which ſtood in force, when <hi>Iohn</hi> writ his Epiſtle, which could not then be the abrogated <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Law.</hi> Then that ſame Commandement, which is broken by tranſgreſsion, is contrarily kept by the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize of obedience.</p>
               <p>This reaſon was alledged of late, at a <hi>Conference;</hi> and had by the aduerſe part, a threefold ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ception taken againſt it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. One, for the terme of keeping the Law, that it is in no mans power to doe it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another, againſt the Argument, from Oppoſition: That, of what commandement the breach is a ſinne, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary keeping thereof is a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and a vertue. Adultery
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16033:32"/> (ſaith hee) is a ſinne, and a breach of the ſeuenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: and yet euery one is a vertuous keeper of it which is no Adulterer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third was againſt that Aſſertion; that <hi>Sin is the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law:</hi> ſithence <hi>Infidelity,</hi> in <hi>not beleeuing in Chriſt,</hi> is a Sin, and yet the Law commandeth not faith in him.</p>
               <p>Whereunto the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,<note place="margin">Men made able by grace to do that which is termed: keeping the the law.</note> that then was made, ſhall now be repeated.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 The firſt faileth of truth, and ſauoreth of ignorance, when it denieth that any man can keepe the Law: For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee impoſsible for men perfectly to doe all that the Law, in ſtrictneſſe, doth as it were, exact; yet they are made able by the vertue of grace, to performe ſuch ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as are acceptable to God:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16033:32"/> and this the ſcripture termeth Keeping; as <hi>Behold I haue</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 5. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>taught you Ordinances and Lawes, as the LORD GOD commanded mee, &amp;c Keep them therefore, and doe them: for that is your wiſdome, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, in the ſight of the people, &amp;c.</hi> So in another place; <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>are they that keepe his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and ſeeke him with their whole heart.</hi> So in the Goſpell, <hi>Bleſſed are they that heare the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 11. 28. 1 Ioh. 3. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>word of GOD, and keepe it</hi> And yet in another place: <hi>and whatſoeuer we aske, we receiue of him, becauſe we keepe his Commandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Touching the ſecond, I ſay, that <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> the hatred and ſhunning of filthineſſe, and the loue and preſeruation of puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſtandeth in oppoſition to Adultery; and not the meere forbearance of the groſſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of it; ſo that euery one
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16033:33"/> doth not obey that Precept, which hath not fallen into the foule fact of incontinencie.</p>
               <p>3. The third hath the moſt ſhew of truth and appearance<note place="margin">Whether faith be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the law? and how.</note> of force: but vpon ſifting it, it will proue fallacious, and to bee of no validity: For, in ſome reſpect (without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) faith cannot bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Law; but hath its place properly and ſolely, in the Goſpell: But in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect it is that, which GOD by his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requireth, and wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but violate his Law, in not yeelding the ſame vnto him. As GOD in his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth freely pardon the ſinnes of his people, by the death and merits of his Sonne apprehended by faith, being as it were the eye, vnto which this wonderfull happineſſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth; ſo this cannot come
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16033:33"/> within the compaſſe of the Law, nor to be expected from it: That, conteined a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of life to ſuch as obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; but no promiſe of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to them that tranſgreſſed it. Saluation proceedeth from Grace alone, through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> reuealed in the Goſpel, and confirmed to his people in the new Teſtament. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo offered, &amp; tendred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs; no man can reiect the ſame without violation of the firſt Commandement, in not giuing to God the honor of his <hi>Attributes;</hi> as of <hi>Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Truth, Power,</hi> &amp; the like. For he doth not chooſe, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Lord to be his God, as by it we are required.</p>
               <p>Who can denie, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer rightly acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord to bee ſuch a one, as in his nature hee is, doth yeeld due obedience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16033:34"/> his Commandement? And <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> taught this publikely, that, <hi>He which hath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>receiued Chriſt his teſtimonie,</hi> (and accordingly beleeueth in him,) <hi>hath ſealed that God is true,</hi> and is as ready to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it, with the profeſsion of his lips, as they, that confirme their deede, by putting their hand, and ſeale vnto it.</p>
               <p>But now, that we may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt<note place="margin">Significant ceremoines cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</note> from digreſsions, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in the proſecution of our point; it will be needfull to exemplifie the matter with ſome particular inſtances, that in caſe a <hi>ſignification</hi> could turne a morall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement into a ceremonial divers of the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould be ſuch.</p>
               <p>There were two pillars ſet<note place="margin">1 King. 7. 22.</note> in the porch of the Temple; the one was called <hi>Lachin,</hi> that is, <hi>He will eſtabliſh:</hi> and the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16033:34"/> other <hi>Boaz;</hi> which ſignifieth, <hi>In him is ſtrength.</hi> Are not theſe repreſentations of Gods all-ſufficiency, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs, &amp; we ought to entertaine a perſwaſion of, by the firſt Commandement? Beſide a great multitude of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ceremonies contained vnder the 2. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, there were diuerſe ſorts of Sacrifices; whereof ſome were offered for actual confeſsions ſome for actuall ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſome for actuall deprecations, ſome for actuall thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings: and many ſuch morall vſes they were deſtinated to, and that by Gods owne ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointment. In the fourth Commandement we haue our aduerſaries on our ſide in this behalfe, who grant, and proue that a Ceremony was thereby preſcribed, ſeing the Seuenth day had in it a ſignification of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16033:35"/> the euerlaſting reſt to come.</p>
               <p>That the reſtraint of blood belonged to the ſixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, we need not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any other teſtimony, then the reaſon, which the Law-maker himſelfe aſsigned<note place="margin">Gen. 9. 4 5. 6.</note> for it, when he ſaid; <hi>Fleſh with the life thereof, that is, with the blood thereof, you ſhall not eat: for ſurely I will require your blood, wherein your liues are: at the hand of every beaſt will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it. And at the hand of a man, even of a mans brother will I require it. Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood bee ſhed: for in the Image of God made he man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And can it be truly gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied, that the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Ielouſie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 5. 12 13.</note> ſo largely ſet downe in one place of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> for the conviction, or clearing of a woman ſuſpected of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is an appurtenance of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16033:35"/> the ſeuenth Commandement? Thither alſo (as it ſeemeth) are to be referred thoſe vncleane iſſues of mans fleſh, the fluxe of naturall ſeed, whereby they were legally polluted, and the<note place="margin">Levit. 15. 2. 3.</note> offerings appointed for their clenſing.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing ſignificant Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies could not alter the nature of theſe vnchangeable Commandements; it is no more probable, that the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Mutations of ſervices alter not the nature of the law.</note> of ſeruices, which is made by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſhould doe it. For the practize and vſage of ſome is ceaſed, and the exerciſe of others is eſtabliſhed, in the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by inſtitution; and yet the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelfe is not varied. If I ſhould bring in, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the <hi>Firſt day of the weeke,</hi> now called the <hi>Lords-day</hi> ſucceeding the former ſeventh day, in the honor, and dignity
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16033:36"/> of it, I ſhould ſeeme to begge the queſtion: I will rather therefore declare it in ſuch ordinances, as are ſubiect, to leſſe oppoſition.</p>
               <p>There was a time, when men obeyed the Second com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, by hearkening to the miniſtery of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and imbracing the doctrine of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who had not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a legall function, but a morall. <hi>To teach Jacob GODS</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut 33. 10</note> 
                  <hi>iudgements, and Iſraell his law. And the Prieſts lips ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>knowledge, and they ſhould ſeeke the law at his mouth: for hee was the meſſenger of the Lord-of-hoſtes.</hi> But <hi>Chriſt</hi> put an end to that calling, and <hi>Aſcending vpon high, led cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 11. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>captiue, and gaue gifts vnto men. (He gaue ſome to be Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors, and teachers &amp;c.</hi> And
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16033:36"/> now, euer ſince that time, his worſhip hath beene celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his people inſtructed according to their doctrine, and miniſtery.</p>
               <p>There was a time, when <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> were the Sacraments of the viſible Church, wherewith it was expedient, that all the people of God, who profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their hope in him, ſhould then be ſigned: But now is <hi>Baptiſme</hi> come into the place of the one; and the <hi>Lord-Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> into the place of the other: all theſe being the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of one, and the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:16033:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> The fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a Morall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O many learned men haue written ſo well on this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that it may ſeeme altogether ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluons, and needleſſe, to make any further addition. And ſo many braines haue beene ſtrained, in deviſing of eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and plotting of ſhifts, to obſcure the cleareneſſe of the cauſe, that it may ſeeme
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16033:37"/> meerely booteleſſe, and to no purpoſe, to beſtow any more travell in the matter. Yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the former good ſucceſſe of their labors, who haue dealt for the Service of God, in this kind, (that many eyes haue beene illightened thereby, although ſome others would ſee nothing,) hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged vs once againe to iuſtifie this Truth ſo much op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pugned; having (as wee thinke) a due calling to the worke, with hope of Gods wonted favor and bleſsing, for the event of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And, for proofe, wee will content our ſelues with few reaſons, and ſpare the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity thereof; not vrging ſo many as we could, nor diſſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of thoſe, as ſlight, and forceleſſe, which we forbeare to repeate.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:16033:38"/>
                  <head>Argument. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> therefore ſhall be the <hi>Firſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALl the Ceremoniall Law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument 1 proving the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the 4 precept. Gal. 3. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>and every part thereof, had the originall, and tooke begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, after man had ſinned, and was added becauſe of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> by way of conviction of guiltineſſe, both to iuſtifie Gods righteouſneſſe, and to drive men to repentance, and for a repreſentation of expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion offered by the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to lead men vnto faith in him, &amp; ſo to magnifie Gods mercy. And this was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of all the Types what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer which the Church of God retained, and vſed, from the fall of our firſt parents, to the reſurrection of our <hi>Bleſſed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16033:38"/> Saviour.</hi> Now the obedience due to the <hi>Fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> hath another maner of foundation: it was not ſo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned, but grounded on the example of God the <hi>Creator,</hi> practized, and propoſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any mention of mans diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and miſery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Argument. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THis fourth</hi> Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument 2. proving the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fourth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</note> participateth with the three other before, and the ſixe next following, in all the prerogatiues, and honors, wherein they goe before al the Leviticall conſtitutions for more glorious promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and eſtabliſhment. They were pronounced by the voice of God himſelfe, vnto the people immediatly: ſo was this. For it is ſaid, that <hi>God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16033:39"/> ſpake all theſe words.</hi> They were<note place="margin">Exod. 20. 10</note> written <hi>in tables of ſtone, by the finger of God,</hi> as it were, euen by the Lord himſelfe: So was this. For it is ſaid. <hi>He wrot</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 10. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>vpon the tables, according, to the firſt writing, the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, which the LORD ſpake vnto you, in the mount, out of the midſt of the fire, in the day of the aſſembly: and the Lord gaue them vnto me. Deut.</hi> 10. 4. They thus written, were put into the Arke. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">1 King 8. 9.</note> 9. So was it alſo with them. For the two Tables being there placed, and it in one of them, muſt needes have place in the ſame, among the reſt.</p>
                  <p>They were written by the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> in the booke of <hi>Exodus,</hi> ioyntly together, without mixture of any other with them: So was this alſo, &amp; ſet in an high place, before all thoſe of the Second Table.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:16033:39"/>
                  <p>Nothing of this is affirmed of the Law conſiſting of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies: God vttered not that, with his owne voyce, neither was it written at all, in the <hi>Two Tables</hi> of ſtone: or put into the <hi>Arke. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 King. 8. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>was in it ſaue the Two Tables of ſtone, which Moſes had put there, at Horeb.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it ioyned in place, with the <hi>Morall</hi> precepts in <hi>Exodus</hi> 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Argument 3.</head>
                  <p>THe moſt neere vnion,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument 3 proving the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the 4 precept.</note> that is betweene this Commandement, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nine, will ſtrongly proue it to be of their number, and one of the ſame nature with them. How often doth the Scripture inculcate this word [<hi>All</hi>], when it ſpeaketh of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16033:40"/> them? as in Deuteronomy.<note place="margin">Deut. 4. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>What nation is there ſo great, that hath ordinances, &amp; Lawes ſo righteous, as</hi> All <hi>this Law, which I ſet before you this day? The Lord hath commanded vs to doe</hi> All <hi>theſe ordinances. This ſhall be our righteouſnes, before the Lord, our God, if wee take heede to keepe</hi> All <hi>theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 24. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>which hee hath commanded vs.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> calleth them [<hi>Ten words</hi>] ſhal we thinke that he meant more or leſſe, then the iuſt number of the Morall precepts? Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when in <hi>Exodus</hi> hee ſaith; <hi>God ſpake</hi> All <hi>theſe words.</hi> And in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> that <hi>He added no more thereto.</hi> If any<note place="margin">Deut. 5. 22.</note> other had beene put to them, they had exceeded that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: if this be none of them, there would be but nine. It is obſervable, that in ſundry places, they are called A <hi>Law;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16033:40"/> The Law;</hi> and <hi>The whole Law</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 10.</note> as in the Epiſtle of <hi>Iames. Whoſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet faile in one point, is guilty of al.</hi> Reaſon teacheth that all the integrall parts of any thing muſt be ſutable to the whole, as the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of them all. As in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body having diverſe members, they are all genuine (as I may ſo ſay) and of the ſame nature, and not forraine and of another kind. The hands, the feete, the legges, and armes, the backe, the loines, and other ioynts of a man are all of one kind of fleſh and bones. And, as this holdeth firme in ſingular, and individuall perſons: ſo the ſame proportion may bee obſerved in the ſeverall <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Creatures. The beaſts haue no beakes, or bils, the birds haue no ſinnes, the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16033:41"/> fiſhes have no hoofes, men have no wings, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And the more yet, to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt this vnion of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi> that it may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, how that they are all of one ſorte, <hi>Moſes</hi> his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie is to bee noted, who ioyneth them all together e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually, without diſparadge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or exception of any one, and acknowledgeth them to be, as it were, ſo many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of one maine Couenant in theſe words. <hi>Then he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto you his Covenant,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>which hee commanded you to do, euen the Ten Commandements; and wrote them vpon two Tables of ſtone.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Argument. 4.</head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument 4. proving, the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the 4. precept.</note>
                  <p>THe maine ends of this Commandement, and the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16033:41"/> religious duties, with warrant and approbation to be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on the Sabbath dayes, ſerue not onely for induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to bring men to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of the moralty thereof but may well be taken for ſolid grounds, and evicting arguments of the certainety of the ſame. That the Sabbath was inſtituted for a memoriall of the worke of Creation fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and not alone for a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of Redemption hoped for; it may eaſily bee collected out of the hyſtory recorded in <hi>Goneſis,</hi> &amp; GODS owne profeſsion, by way of a reaſon, at the publiſhing of that precept in <hi>Exodus.</hi> For why doth he ſo ſolemnly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and recken vp the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thoſe eminent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>The Heauen, The Earth,</hi> and <hi>The Sea, </hi> but that his wil was, in the celebration of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16033:42"/> that day, to haue them medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated on, for his praiſe, and honor?</p>
                  <p>And the accuſtomed vſe of publike meetings, and therein of reading the Scriptures to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with preaching, and hearing of Sermons, <hi>Iames</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Moſes of old</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 15. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>time, hath in every Citie them that preach him, ſeeing he is read in the Synagogue every Sabbath day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the Goſpell, much graced that practize, with his owne example. For (as <hi>Luke</hi> teſtifieth) <hi>Hee went, as his cuſtome was, into the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, vpon the Sabbath day &amp; ſtood vp to read, and preached</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 4 15. 13. &amp;. ſeqq.</note> 
                     <hi>vnto them, out of the Prophet Eſaias:</hi> as is more at large to be ſeene in the ſtory. Now the Synagogues were not the places, wherein they met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16033:42"/> for the ſolemnizing of the Leviticall feaſts; but the Temple. For all the males, that could, were enioyned there to appeare before the <hi>LORD,</hi> on thoſe dayes.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, the internall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the minde and heart,<note place="margin">Iſay 58. 13.</note> as holy meditations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which <hi>Eſaias</hi> teacheth to be meete, and neceſſary for the ſanctifying of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; were ever to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in truth, and verity: and not ſymbollically, for ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation onely.</p>
                  <p>This time was likewiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, as GOD expreſly<note place="margin">Deut. 5. 14. 15.</note> profeſſeth, in one place; for the exerciſing of mercy, in granting reſt, and refreſhing to the bodyes of ſervants, and inferiours, whether they were natives, or aliens, Iewes, or Gentiles; of whom many
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16033:43"/> might haue no admiſſion to the Tabernacle, Temple, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, or Sacrifices, or to any ſuch like Ordinances.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Argument. 5.</head>
                  <p>LAſtly, the ſtability, and<note place="margin" type="runSum">Argument 5 proving the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the forth Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</note> durableneſſe of it doth firmely argue the moralitie, that is in it. For, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the legall ſhadowes are ſtill to be remembred, and the body repreſented by them, is eternall: yet the practize, and vſage of them was to giue place, and to ſurceaſe, after their accompliſhment, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling. But the practicall keeping of the Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, (whereof the fourth is one) is not determined, but reall obedience is evermore
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16033:43"/> due to each of them, aſwell now, as before <hi>Chriſt</hi> his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and that according to his owne teſtimony, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, with a threatning and a promiſe annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto; as the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> thus<note place="margin">Matth. 5. 19.</note> recordeth the matter. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall breake one of theſe leaſt Commandements, and teach men ſo, ſhall be called the leaſt in the kingdome of heaven: But who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall obſerue and teach them, the ſame ſhall be called great in the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Where Three things,<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 19. Expounded</note> touching our point in hand, are conſiderable.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. One, What is meant by <hi>Theſe Commandements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Another, What is meant by <hi>Theſe leaſt Commandements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. And the Third; How long this ſentence of our <hi>Saviour</hi> doth ſtand in force.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Firſt, Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:16033:44"/> (an impartiall interpretter,) ſhall informe vs of, in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this Text, on this wiſe. <hi>Here Chriſt ſpeaketh, by name, of the precepts for wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living, even of the Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dements; according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript whereof all the children of GOD ought to lead their lives.</hi> And this ſenſe is made very manifeſt, by the verſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; wherein the <hi>LORD JESVS</hi> himſelfe, againſt the falſe, and phantaſticall gloſſes of the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> doth give a ſound expoſition of certaine particular Commandements, as of the Sixth, the Seventh, and the Third.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. In the next place; by <hi>The Leaſt</hi> is vnderſtood any one of the Ten, that ſhould be ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by diſ-eſteeme, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous tranſgreſsion; as if it had not ioynt holineſſe, and authoritie with all the reſt,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16033:44"/> when no conſcience is made of faithfull obedience to it.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. And concerning the laſt inquiry or conſideration; It behooueth every one to know that this ſpeech of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not confined to his own dayes during the time of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall life and corporall abode here vpon earth, vntill his death and reſurrection: but to be extended to all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages, &amp; future times. For otherwiſe Saint <hi>Iames</hi> would not ſo long afterwards haue ſaid; <hi>Whoſoever ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet faile in</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>one point is guilty of all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now we are come to the ſifting of thoſe obiections, which Maſter <hi>Broad,</hi> and other our aduerſaries in this cauſe, doe vrge againſt vs that a due and iuſt anſwer may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly be made thereunto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:16033:45"/>
                  <head>Obiection 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt is from Texts of Scripture. GOD calleth the</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection 1 againſt the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fourth Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> 
                     <hi>Sabbath a</hi> Signe, <hi>Exod. 31. 17. It is a Signe betweene me, and the children of Iſraell for ever. Chriſt likeneth the Sabbath to</hi> Sacrifices. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 7. Paul <hi>termes it a</hi> Shadow. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 17.</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>As good a ſhew as the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of theſe places doth make, yet if they be reduced into the forme of an argument a fallacy will be diſcovered therein, and the point in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion found vnconcluded. The moſt, that can be inforced out of them, is this</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whatſoever was a Signe, a Sacrifice, and a Shadow, was not morall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:16033:45"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But the former Sabbath was a Signe, a Sacrifice, and a ſhadow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore the former Sabbath was not morall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But doth the controuerſie betweene vs conſiſt in this? Should not we looke for this concluſion: <hi>Therfore the fourth Commandement is not morall?</hi> But we will giue a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reſolution to the Texts obiected. As for that Twelfth of <hi>Matthew.</hi> It concerneth not the weekly Sabbath, as we ſhall ſhew in the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Touching the other Two. Firſt we denie the Sabbath to haue beene originally a <hi>Signe,</hi> and a <hi>Shadow.</hi> It might be meerely morall, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and yet afterward have a ſignification put into it. For at the firſt inſtitution, there were no <hi>Iſralites,</hi> whom it ſhould diſtinguiſh as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of GOD, from all other
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16033:46"/> nations, neither was it ſimply a <hi>Signe</hi> at any time, but in ſome reſpect: neither was it totally a <hi>Signe,</hi> but in part on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for there were many other vſes of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Commandement and not about the day And the <hi>Sum</hi> thereof is, That GODS cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and ſelected time be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably kept, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly beſtowed in his worſhip. That there ſhould be ſome legall vſe of one day, as there was of the former <hi>Seuenth:</hi> And ſome <hi>Evangilicall</hi> reſpect in another as there is in the now eſtabliſhed <hi>LORDS-day.</hi> It is rather a quality in the ſervices commanded, then of the ſubſtance and eſſence of the Commandement it ſelfe. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:16033:46"/>
                  <head>Obiection 2.</head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection 2. againſt the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of fourth precept an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Were the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Morall, it were greater then any Commandement, in the Second Table: being greater, it ſhould be preferred before it. Whereas indeed it ought to giue place to a branch onely of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, in the ſecond Table. For a few ought to ſave his neighbors Goods from burning; though hee ſpent the whole day therein; and neither reſted, nor went to the aſſemblies; and were it morall to ſanctifie the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and a City on fire; And a Iew could not both ſaue his neighbors goods, and ſanctifie the Sabbath: Hee ought to haue ſanctified the Sabbath; and to haue ſuffered his neighbors goods to periſh: which ſeeing he might not doe, it is manifeſt, that to ſanctifie the Sabbath was not morall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:16033:47"/>
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Iuſt exceptions may, and muſt be taken againſt this reaſon: for it is more then one way faulty; as in this; That the fourth Commandement is made inferior to the eight becauſe in a caſe of neceſsitie ſome workes of the fourth are to be omitted in the inſtant, for the prevention of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie in our brothers eſtate. Now in this caſe, there is no compariſon betweene the two Commandements, which of them ſhould be the greater, or the leſſe. But of actions, which ſhould be firſt, or laſt; or which ſhould be performed, or neceſſarily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, at that ſeaſon. Some eſpeciall, and important du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Second Table may be more acceptable, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16033:47"/> then thoſe of an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our nature, of the firſt. When <hi>Obadiah</hi> preſerued the liues of an hundred Prophets, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed a better ſervice to GOD, then he could haue done by reading a Chapter, or two, in the Law, or by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an ordinary prayer to him. Our Adverſaries will confeſſe, that all externall actions of religion, as ſinging of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> making of prayers hearing of ſermons, &amp; the like (though <hi>Morall</hi>) giue place to workes of mercy, in ſuch caſes. But (ſay they) becauſe I may firſt doe the worke of mercy, and afterwards wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip GOD. And ſo (ſay I) I may ſhew that mercy, and afterwards finiſh the remnant of the Sabbath, in ſacred ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes; or elſe ſome others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards: for that my worke tendeth not to the aboliſhing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16033:48"/> of the day, or of my due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of it. And this is alſo worthily to be taxed, that they ſet the workes of mercy, and the ſanctifying of the Sabbath, as oppoſits: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they are ſubordinate, and one of them a meanes of the other, and a commendable practize thereof, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> witneſſeth <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 12.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection 3.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Prieſts in the Temple</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection 3. againſt the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the 4 precept anſwered. <hi>Thomas Broad, his manuſcript part. 1. cap. 1 &amp; cap. 2. arg 3.</hi>
                     </note> (Mat. 12. 5.) <hi>preferred a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, before the Fourth Commandement: for they offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sacrifices, as was inioyned. Thus they laboured in killing beaſts: whereby they prophaned the Sabbath, and were blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. And the Diſciples pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eares of corne, and rubbing them in their hands, on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, prophaned it. And ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16033:48"/> did the man, that tooke vp his bed, on that day. Whereas, in the iudgement of the learned, the breach of the morall law is ſinne. And therefore the morall law may not be broken, to ſaue the liues of all mankind. Evill muſt not be done, that good may come thereof. Yea GOD himſelfe cannot giue a man leaue to breake a morall Commandement; as to ſteale, murder, or lie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>This kind of reaſoning ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth very vnſavoury, as wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both good ſmell, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: by making one of GODS ſervices to be a proper, and direct violation of another: as though <hi>GODS ſpirit</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed contrarieties in the ſame Subiect. For, by taking the word (<hi>Prophaning</hi>) of the Sabbath literally, as here our
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16033:49"/> adverſary doth: it will follow that thoſe ſacred miniſters of God, in the <hi>Temple,</hi> who ſhuld haue beene moſt holily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, did exerciſe as little holineſſe in their callings, on that day, and aſmuch infringe that precept of the LORD, <hi>Remember that thou keepe holy the Sabbath day:</hi> as they, that were moſt devoyd of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> dealeth more kindly with them, in his <hi>Annotations,</hi> ſaying. <hi>The Prieſts, doing the worke of GOD, on the Sabbath day, did not yet violate the Law. And therefore, by the Law of the Sabbath, all workes, without any exception, are not forbidden.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The latter part of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, (which, hee ſaith, is grounded on the iudgement of the learned) is true. i. <hi>That a morall Commandement cannot be broken, without ſinne,</hi> but not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16033:49"/> well applyed. Diſpoſe it into forme, and let the <hi>Minor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> ſpeake out, and it will tell a flat vntruth: For ſo it muſt be.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No morall law may be broken without ſinne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be broken, without ſinne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is no morall law.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This [<hi>Broken, Breach, and Breaking</hi>] ſoundeth harſhly, as arguing contempt; or, at the leaſt, a neglect of due care to performe that, which is inioyned. Now this cannot be offered to the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement; neither could it to any of the Ceremoniall conſtitutions, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyaltie to the <hi>Law-giuer,</hi> whoſe will is thereby diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed. Omiſsions there may be of that, which ſeemeth to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16033:50"/> be required, and practize of that, which, in ſtrictneſſe, hath an appearance of a prohibition: and yet, by the true meaning of the law, or with alowance from him, which made the Law: hee, which doth ſo omit, or prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, may therein be faultleſſe and praiſe worthy. But this is not proper to the Fourth Commandement; but falleth out aſwell, in other morall Precepts. If any man now ſhould marry his own ſiſter; it could not be but a grieuous and inceſtuous tranſgreſsion of the Seuenth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and yet it was not ſo in <hi>Adams</hi> immediate chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Stealing is a violation of the Eight Commandement: and yet the Iſralits ſpoyling of the Egyptians of their iewels, and other ornaments, were not in the ſtate of<note place="margin">Exod. 12. 36</note>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:16033:50"/> theeues. Murder is an hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous breach of the Sixth Commandement, and all vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence forbidden by it: and yet <hi>Moſes</hi> did not fault in kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<note place="margin">Exod. 2. 12</note> the Egyptian: Nor <hi>Phinehas</hi> in ſlaying the <hi>Midi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anite,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Num. 25. 8.</note> and Iſraelitiſh woman. Nor hee, that in the booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> wounded the <hi>Prophet</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 King. 20. 37.</note> of GOD, being a righteous man. For all theſe had their warrant and direction from the LORD.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection. 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All the morall precepts are</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection 4 againſt the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fourth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> 
                     <hi>written in the heart of man; and the obſervation of them is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law of nature. But ſo is not that of the Fourth Commandement: for nature doth not teach men weekely to keepe day of ſeven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:16033:51"/>
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>To this we ſay, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is confirmed to be <hi>Morall,</hi> becauſe it is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the law, and light of nature; as may be ſeene in the cuſtomes of Idolaters, both in the Scriptures, and by<note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> common experience, among the heathen, who vſed to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate feaſts, and ſolemne times, to their GODS, with a religious devotion. But it is ſaid;</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That ſo Churches ſhould bee alſo, by the law of nature; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they built Temples like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to their Idols.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>That doth not neceſſarily
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16033:51"/> follow; foraſmuch as the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnites of their feaſts were the occaſion of their Temples and ſo the one was, as it were a conſectary of the other. As it was by the law of nature, to ſolemnize feſtiuites to their GODS: ſo by the ſame they were moved to aſſemble together, &amp; iointly to do their ſervice: hereupon they ſtood in need of fit places; thoſe places then they made decent and comely, and afterwards very beautifull, and pompous whereby, being led by ſenſe, and ſuch goodly ſights, they waxed ſuperſtitious of them; eſpecially by the Statues, and images of their Gods, being therein placed. So that exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall motiues induced them ſo highly to eſteeme of, and as it were, to adore their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; whereunto they grew more, and more, by Cuſtome,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16033:52"/> examples, and deluſions. But the doubt yet remaineth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolued, how nature ſhould direct vs to the ſanctifying of one day in ſeuen, or in any ſet number, and that to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly this, or that day of the the weeke; eſpecially varied, and not at the laſt the ſame, which was obſerued at the firſt. For reſolution whereof we will build on <hi>Zanchius</hi> his foundation, (although hee be produced as a witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our cauſe, by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries) which he doth lay before vs. <hi>It is the wil of GOD (and according to the rule of nature, and reaſon,) to ſanctifie ſome time to GOD.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And then will this follow, that he is, by inſtitution, to chuſe, or change the time, at his owne pleaſure: and that the time ſo ſet, choſen by him be duly ſet apart, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:16033:52"/> of his worſhip. For he commended the ſeuenth day to the Iſraelits, not onely by edict, but by reaſon, alſo and the force of equitie, ſaying, it was <hi>The Sabbath of the LORD their GOD,</hi> and that <hi>Which hee had bleſſed,</hi> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them an example of by practize. Now whatſoeuer reaſon doth apprehend as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, muſt needs be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the light of nature: as the LORD teſtifieth of the Gentiles, that they, <hi>Would not ſpoile their GODS:</hi> that<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 8.</note> is, take, or detaine any thing from them: and this they learned onely from nature.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection. 5.</head>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection 5. againſt the morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fourth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>
                  <p>The obſeruation, and keeping of this Commandement is of no antiquity: Adam being thruſt out of Paradiſe, neither he, nor
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16033:53"/> his poſterity ſanctified any day, in an holy reſt, for ought that we doe certainly find, or may pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bably coniecture. The Jewes acknowledge that they doe not read, of <hi>Abrahams</hi> keeping the Sabbath. And I may adde, neither of any others keeping, or breaking it, both before, and a good while ſince <hi>Abrahams</hi> time It is not likely that <hi>Iacob</hi> whiles hee ſerved his vncle <hi>Laban,</hi> an Idolater; or any of the Iſralites all the while, they were ſo cruelly oppreſſed: reſted from worke every Seventh day. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs were not commanded to ſanctifie any day. And had the godly Iſraelites vnder <hi>Pharo,</hi> or the Iewes vnder the King of Babylon, and Chriſtians vnder the Heathen gouernors, refuſed to worke, one day in ſeuen, it would have bred great ſtirres, coſt many men their lives; and no doubt, hyſtories would haue beene full of it.</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:16033:53"/>
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Here is great ſtrength of immagination, but ſmall force of reaſon. For all the examples vrged, are at the moſt, but coniecturall, and the grounds thereof very weake. If <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> and the other <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> keeping of all the other Commandements, had beene particularly recorded, and this alone by name vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken of, there had beene ſome probability in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But no mention is made of many ſeruices; which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe they vndoubtedly performed.</p>
                     <p>And for the Iſraelites in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> if they did not reſt on the Sabbath, the queſtion is, whether it were not a fault in them; at the leaſt of infirmity and weakneſſe. And that fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16033:54"/> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, if there were any ſuch, muſt needs bee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged vnlawfull: for that was after the law was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. And that the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sabbath was not confined within the bounds of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Iſraell;</hi> it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the 16. <hi>Chap.</hi> of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles, ver.</hi> 13. and in diuers other places. But wee haue Scriptures, which will yeeld ſtronger probability, for the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of it, that it was obſerued before <hi>Iſraell</hi> came into the Wilderneſſe. Sure it is, that it was kept, before it was proclaimed on Mount <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai:</hi> for they were inioyned in conſcience of it, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the gathering of <hi>Manna</hi> on the <hi>Seuenth day;</hi> as it ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth in the 16. of <hi>Exodus.</hi> And it is not likely that then
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:16033:54"/> was the firſt inſtitution of it: for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh, as of a thing knowne to them before: and in rebuking of the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsors he ſaith; <hi>How long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Exod. 16. 23. 29.</note> 
                        <hi>you to keepe my commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and my Lawes?</hi> But that wee may not be ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceited in making ſuch a Collection out of this place; wee haue Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> of the ſame minde with vs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Some</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are of</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Willet</hi> on Exod. 16. 20 <hi>Queſt. 34.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>opinion, that the Iſraelites began firſt now to keepe the Sabbath; and that this Precept was to continue vntill the comming of the Meſſiah: But this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath no ground, or good warrant: for,</hi> Moſes <hi>ſpeaketh of the Sabbath,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:16033:55"/> as of a thing well knowne:</hi> Tomorrow is the reſt of the Sabbath. <hi>And to what end elſe ſhould the people bee ſo ready to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a double portion, for the ſixth day, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, before</hi> Moſes <hi>had yet ſpoken any thing of the reſt therof. Therefore it is more then probable, that the Sabbath was kept of ancient time, among the people of GOD, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the example of GOD himſelfe, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, after the Creation fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:16033:55"/> in ſixe dayes, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Seuenth: which obſeruation was deliuered by godly tradition, from Adam to his poſterity: for ſeeing that the Church had from the beginning, a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, &amp; externall worſhip of God, it could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bee, but that they had alſo a certaine time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed, wherein to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſeruice of GOD: And then what time was more fit, then that which GOD had ſanctified by his owne example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:16033:56"/>
                     <p>And wee are not to ſeeke of a ſtrong probability, that may be gathered out of the New Teſtament, that the Sabbath hath beene in vſe among the godly, from the beginning; or hath not beene alwayes out of vſe, vntill <hi>Moſes</hi> his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, although it bee not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſo affirmed. For the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth intimate ſo<note place="margin">Heb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the Fourth to the <hi>Hebrewes:</hi> where hee proueth, that the reſt ſpoken of by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> in the Ninety and Fifth Pſalme (which the vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers are threatened to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred of) muſt needs bee meant of that which is to bee found in heauen; as being not by them, as yet entred into. For thus he reaſoneth by way of diſtribution: Either hee ſpake of the reſt of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> or the <hi>Reſt</hi> of the <hi>Seuenth-Day,</hi> or of the <hi>Reſt</hi> of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:16033:56"/> the life to come.</p>
                     <p>But hee did not ſpeake of either of the two former Therefore hee ſpake of that, which is in the life to come.</p>
                     <p>Now for proofe of the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi> Why may it not be vnderſtood of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan?</hi> Becauſe <hi>Ioſuah</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them entrance into that, before <hi>Dauids</hi> dayes. And why not of the <hi>Reſt</hi> of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth-Day?</hi> Becauſe an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance was made into that; ſhortly after the foundation of the world, when GOD had once finiſhed his workes, and reſted. Now if the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> had taken its beginning in the wilderneſſe, how could the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> tenent be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied?</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:16033:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 4.</hi> All conſecrated time, is the obſeruation of the Fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment?</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Poſition may ſeeme peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to bee of ſo great a latitude, as that it would require a large Induction of particulars, for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and bee very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult therefore to bee made
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:16033:57"/> good. But the verity that is in it, will be eaſily apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of them, that ſhall aſſent to certaine truthes, which, without obſtinate peruerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, cannot bee gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The Firſt whereof is, That it hath ſtood with the wiſedome, and good pleaſure of GOD, to chooſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to ſanctifie certaine ſet dayes, for the exerciſe of his owne worſhip, by his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their Saluation. And in this reſpect they are called the <hi>Feaſts</hi> of the LORD, in <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> and other places of<note place="margin">Leuit. 23. 2.</note> Scripture.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The next is; That by the equity of the <hi>Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> theſe dayes ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled out and ſeparated from common vſe, by the LORD, ſhould bee ſet apart to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:16033:58"/> and acknowledged ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bee his peculiar right; according to that of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; If thou turne away thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay. 58. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>foot from the Sabbath, from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy will on my holi-day; and call the Sabbath a delight, to conſecrate it as glorious to the LORD, nor doing thy owne waies, nor ſeeking thy owne will, nor ſpeaking a vaine word: then ſhalt thou delight in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The third is, That, if it be found, that any dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Seuenth,</hi> in regard of ſuch hallowing, be appendent, and belonging to that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: it will well fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that all of the ſame ſort, &amp; which are deſtinated to the ſame vſe, are alſo, in the ſame reſpect, and by the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, ſo to bee reputed and thought of.</p>
               <p>Now, that we may further inſiſt vpon this laſt, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:16033:58"/> look into that 23. of<note place="margin">All the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne feaſtes in the law iſſued from the ſame fountaine that the ſeuenth day did. Levit. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Lev:</hi> &amp; there we may ſee, that the other ſacred Feſtiuities in time iſſued out of the ſame fountaine that the <hi>Seuenth-Day</hi> did; although it was by farre, the <hi>faireſt ſtreame,</hi> and they, in compariſon of it, like vnto <hi>ſmall Brooks,</hi> or <hi>little Ril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets.</hi> Both it, and all the reſt are termed the [<hi>Feaſts of the LORD:</hi>] The name of [<hi>Sabbath</hi>] is common with it to all the ſolemne daies, as it were to be celebrated with holy aſſemblies. And who of iudgement doth not perceiue, that theſe titles, termes, names, and formes of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration are comprehended within the compaſſe of the <hi>Fourth Commandement?</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue wee the Law alone, and <hi>Moſes</hi> to miniſter vnto vs matter, for the proofe of this point: but in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:16033:59"/> alſo, and from <hi>Chriſt</hi> his owne words, wee ſhall finde plaine euidence for it That in the Twelfth of <hi>Mathew,</hi> touching the <hi>Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 1.</note> of eares of corne on the <hi>Sabbath-Day,</hi> reprehended by the Phariſees, doth ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly concerne the breach, or keeping of the <hi>Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> that I know not any one, that is contrarily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded. Yea, our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries doe not onely confeſſe it, but vrge and inforce it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Morality of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> Mr. <hi>Broad</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">In his three queſtions. Pag. 5.</note> our profeſſed Oppoſite, ſhall bee the man, whom wee will call to witneſſe, in this caſe; whoſe teſtimony is thus.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <hi>There are pregnant texts e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to proue, that the Sabbath was a ſhadow or Ceremonie; and conſequently, that the Fourth Commandement is more ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:16033:59"/> then thereſt: as that Text, Mat. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. [But if you had knowne, what this meaneth, I I will haue mercy, and not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, yee would not haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the guiltleſſe.] Here he likeneth the obſeruation of the Sabbath to the offering of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>But how if it appeare, that this corne was not pluckt on the <hi>Seuenth-Day,</hi> nor that, here pleaded for by the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies?</hi> How if it fall out, that this act was done at one of their ſolemnities, on the laſt day of a ſolemne feaſt? will not this bee inferred vpon it, that the <hi>Ceremoniall Sabbaths</hi> came vnder the <hi>Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> and not that the <hi>Morall Sabbath</hi> was cònui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to bee in the nature of a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:16033:60"/> Sacrifice, by this place? Now for the auerring of what I haue ſaid, it will be ſufficient to bring <hi>Luke</hi> as an Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of <hi>Mathew,</hi> touching the Circumſtance of the time; who, in this manner, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it: <hi>And it came to paſſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luc 6. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>on the ſecond Sabbath after the firſt, that hee went through the corne-fields; and his Diſciples plucked the eares of corne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And here doe I appeale to the iudgement of all learned Diuines: Whether [<hi>The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <hi>Sabbath after the firſt</hi>] can bee otherwiſe vnderſtood, then of one of the <hi>Leuiticall Holi-dayes,</hi> which (by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the ſeaſon, in that corne was then ripe vpon the ground) ſeemeth to bee the <hi>Seuenth-Day</hi> of the feaſt of <hi>Vnleuened-Bread,</hi> and the two and twentieth of the firſt Moneth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:16033:60"/>
                  <head>Obiection.</head>
                  <p>But this point aſwell as the former, is excepted againſt, and that by colour of reaſon: for thoſe that are againſt vs, ſtriue to make the Sabbath, and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth-Day, and all that is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be reciprocall, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertible: as that the Sabbath ſhould be none, but that Seuenth-Day, and that Seuenth-Day ſhould only be the Sabbath. So that no other time, either then preſent, or which in future ages ſhould be; could haue any place, in that precept.</p>
                  <p>For, This Queſtion <hi>(ſay they)</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Broad,</hi> in his three queſtions. <hi>pag. 10.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>may well be demanded:</hi> How ſhall the Fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being deliuered in forme of words, binde vs to ſanctifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny day, but onely the Seuenth? Suppoſe that Chriſt had ſaid to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:16033:61"/> his Diſciples; Remember the day of Reſurrection, to ſanctifie it. Sixe dayes of the weeke you ſhall labour, and doe all that you haue to doe: but the firſt day is the day of Reſurrection: in it you ſhall doe, &amp;c. <hi>How ſhould this Commandement binde vs to ſanctifie any day, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the firſt, the day of Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. So GOD ſaying;</hi> Remember the Sabbath (or day of reſt) to ſanctifie it. Sixe daies ſhalt thou labour and doe all thou haſt to doe: but the Seuenth is the Sabbath, &amp;c. How ſhould this Commandement binde vs to ſanctifie any day, but onely the Seuenth-Day, wherein GOD reſted, and which the Iewes ſanctified?</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>For reſolution hereof, I referre them to the generall
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:16033:61"/> rule of direction, that * Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter<note place="margin">We are not tyed to the Iewes Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, by the 4. Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> 
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> giueth, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtanding of all the Commandements; which is this.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>There is alwayes more</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Inſtit. lib. 2. cap. 8. Sect. 8.</note> 
                        <hi>meant in the Precepts and prohibitions, then in words is expreſſed. And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly there are manifeſt Tropes (whereby one part is put for the reſt) in al the Commandements: that he ſhall make himſelfe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be laughed at, who confineth the ſenſe to the ſtrictneſſe of the words.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By ſuch curioſity and nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all ſuperſtitious traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and fancies might bee
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:16033:62"/> freed from the cenſure of the <hi>Second Commandement:</hi> ſeeing it forbiddeth nothing expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly but the making and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images. Neither would the worſhipping of all Images bee there forbidden, but of thoſe onely, which men haue made to themſelues: So that the leaſt part of Idolatry would bee thereby reſtrained. And might not a wrangling Atheiſt picke a quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to cauill at it, thus? How ſhall wee Gentiles bee perſwaded, that the Lord is our GOD, or be induced to deuote our ſelues to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or to thinke that his Commandements are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to vs; ſince hee ſpake to them whom <hi>hee brought out of the Land of Egypt,</hi> where wee neuer were, nor our Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors before vs? And yet wee
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:16033:62"/> know, that the <hi>Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement</hi> doth condemne all humane inuentions, and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip: And the Firſt is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to all his people, of what Nation, Kindred, or Country ſoeuer. And why then ſhould the <hi>Fourth</hi> be girded in ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly? </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:16033:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> The LORDS-Day, is a conſecrated time of Diuine Inſtitution, &amp; immutable.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ound Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and good diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth teach men, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and difference, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer all that may bee ſpoken: but ſo much as will proue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall and ſolide: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although many proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons might be produced,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:16033:63"/> to giue ſome light to the cauſe wee haue in hand; yet it being of ſuch weight &amp; importance as it is, will ſafelieſt be ſetled<note place="margin">The Lords day proued to be of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</note> on ſuch a ſure, and firme foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as may ſecure the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from dread of any demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition or downfall: And ſuch an one it hath in the <hi>Reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> where the Scripture honoureth this day with the glorious Title, and that poſſeſsiuely vttered, of the LORDS-Day, which<note place="margin">Reuel. 1. 10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> publiſheth to the world, euen to the end of the world, that it is not of an ordinary or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ranke, with all the other dayes of the Weeke; but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for ſome more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent employment. There is<note place="margin">Note this.</note> nothing to bee found (for ought I remember) in all the New Teſtament, that by the Spirit of GOD is aſcribed to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and hee thereinto
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:16033:64"/> intituled, in regard of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer the Church but it is ſacred and holy, and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for holy vſes; as <hi>His Word, Col. 3. 16. His Goſpell, Mar. 1. 1. His miniſtry &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, 1 Tim. 1. 12. His Grace, Rom. 16. 24. His Spirit, Gal. 4. 6. His Supper, 1 Cor. 18. 20 His Bread and Cup, 1 Cor. 11. 27. His Table, 1 Cor. 10. 21. His Church, Eph.</hi> 5. 23. And why then ſhould <hi>His Day</hi> alone be defrauded of the honour of<note place="margin">In what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects a day is ſaid to be the Lords day.</note> holineſſe? Let vs proceed a little farther, and inquire why, and for what cauſe it is in this place called by the name of the LORDS-Day. Either it is becauſe it belongeth vnto him by right of Creation: Or for that ſome notable work is appointed to bee wrought in it, by way of deſtination, (as in that ſenſe, or the like, where it is ſaid; <hi>The day of the Lord</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 2.</note>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:16033:64"/> 
                  <hi>ſhall come euen as a thiefe in the night:</hi>) Or by vertue of his ſetting it apart through <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is not termed here, in reſpect of the firſt cauſe: For ſo all times are alike his; as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 74. 16. 17.</note> ſaying; <hi>The day is thine, the night alſo is thine; thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the light, &amp; the ſun. Thou haſt made Summer, and winter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what certaine intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence ſhould the Churches haue receiued from the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,</hi> touching the time, when thoſe great things were revealed vnto him; if he had told them, that it was in a day of GODS making?</p>
               <p>And in reſpect of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond it could not be. For that intendeth a time yet to come. And therefore it muſt be meant of the Laſt; That it is ſo denominated, by reaſon
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:16033:65"/> of that choice, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath made of it by <hi>Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We haue many learned writers, of principall note, conſenting with vs, in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this place to this point. Some by way of <hi>Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> and <hi>declaration;</hi> as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Beza:</hi> Some by way of <hi>Proofe,</hi> and <hi>Confirmation;</hi> as <hi>Peter Martyr:</hi> Some by way of <hi>Diſputation;</hi> as <hi>Doctor Whitakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> doth, in this<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza</hi> Annot <hi>in Apoc. 1. 10.</hi>
                  </note> maner, deliuer his iudgement.</p>
               <p>Iohn <hi>termeth that the LORDS-day, which</hi> Paul <hi>calleth the firſt day of the weeke;</hi> 1. Cor. 16. 2. Act. 20. 7. <hi>Vpon which day it appeareth, that the Chriſtians were wont to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:16033:65"/> aſſemble together, As the Iewes met on the Sabbath in the Synagogue. So that it may appeare, that the Fourth Commandement, for the ſanctifying of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Seventh day, ſo farre as touched the old Sabbath; and the Legall rites, was Ceremoniall: But remaineth, for the worſhip of GOD, a precept of the vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Morall Law, &amp; ſuch a one, as is perpetuall, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this life. And that Sabbath ſtood from the Creation of the world, to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:16033:66"/> the Reſurrection of Chriſt: which, ſeeing it is another Creation of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other world; (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſpeake) then out of doubt, by the appointment of the Holy-Ghoſt to the Apoſtles, in ſtead of the Sabbath, which was for the former age, or that ſeuenth day was choſen the firſt day of the new world, wherein, not that corporall, or corruptible light, which was created the firſt day of the old world: but that which is heauenly and eternal, hath
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:16033:66"/> ſhined vpon vs. And therefore the aſſemblies of the LORDS-day, (which</hi> Iuſtine Martyr <hi>alſo expreſſely mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, in</hi> Apolog. 2.) <hi>are of Apoſtolicall, and truly Divine tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> hath this<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 2.</note> ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As by the appointment of the Law, the Sabbath was celebrated to keepe freſh in memory the making of the world: So now is the LORDS-day for vſe, to keepe freſh the memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of Chriſt his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:16033:67"/> and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to confirme the hope of our owne reſurrection. But, when this change was made, we haue it not expreſſely ſet downe in the holy Scriptures: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of S. Iohn there is expreſſe mention made of the LORDS-day.</hi> Cap. 1. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor Whitakers,</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertia tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio de Die Dominico non eſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> nam in ſcripturae habetur nempè Apoc. 1. 10.</hi>
                  </note> the perfection of the <hi>Scripture</hi> againſt humane tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, affirmeth; that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The LORDS-day is no vnwritten tradition: for that it is found in the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:16033:67"/> Scripture, even in the first of the Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sithence then that this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">The Lords-day is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable.</note> day is founded on the Law and ratified by the Goſpell, it will conſequently follow that that will hold its ſtability, whiles they retaine their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie; and that will be as long, as the Sunne is in the firmament, and the heauens aboue the earth. For <hi>The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>word of the LORD endureth for ever.</hi> And curſed be that<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8.</note> perſon, whether man, or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, that ſhall attempt any innovation againſt it. We muſt not imagine, that an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinace, ſo well, and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically warranted, may be ſubiect to abrogation, or change. And therfore who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer goeth about to repreſſe the obſeruation of it, doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt an execrable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:16033:68"/> by robbing GOD, and his <hi>Church</hi> of ſo glorious an ornament. And, if any man would take vpon him, to make an alteration, by transferring it to another day, he ſhould play <hi>Ieroboams</hi> part, who neglected the time and place preſcribed by the LORD, for his worſhip, and ſervice, and <hi>Offered vpon the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 12. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Altar, which he had made in Bethell, the fifteenth day of the Eight Moneth, (even in the moneth, which he had forged of his owne heart,) and made a ſolemne feaſt vnto the Children of Iſraell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then it is not in mans power, to aboliſh, or remoue the <hi>LORDS-day:</hi> and it is as certaine, that the LORD, will not doe it. For it is one of the immoveables ſpoken of by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>which remaines after that once
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:16033:68"/> Shaking of the heaven, and earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the motiue of it is du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and everlaſting, even the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> who can never poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fall backe againe into his graue: Neither can any thing ſurmount it in glory, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, as that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof ſhould put out or darken the honorable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of it.</p>
               <p>And now an Anſwer is to be made to that, which is excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt this Poſition, and whatſoeuer hath beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the defenſe thereof, and the contrary reaſons on the other ſide come to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How ſhall we know, that the LORDS-day is the Sabbath which we keepe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:16033:69"/>
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>By knowing that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,<note place="margin">The firſt day of the weeke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to bee the Lords day that is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> which we keepe, is that which was then the firſt day of the weeke; and by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the firſt day of the weeke was the day of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> and by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the day of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>reſurrection</hi> gaue denominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that, which is our Sabbath, and cauſed it to be called the <hi>LORDS-day,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is to be intended, that theſe <hi>Seuen Churches</hi> knew what day it was, and likewiſe all others of that time. For ſhall we thinke that <hi>Iohn</hi> would ſo ſlighty deſcribe ſo glorions a viſion, (of ſuch moment for the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> vntill the ſecond comming of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) in that ambiguous maner, and by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:16033:69"/> ſuch a darke circumſtance, as they were altogether vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with? The matter concerned them then, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Churches,</hi> that then were, and thoſe, that were next to ſucceed: and all, that haue beene ever ſince: and theſe of our dayes: and thoſe which ſhall come after, as long as the world ſtandeth.</p>
                     <p>The ioynt, and vniforme practize of ſo many <hi>Churches,</hi> in ſolemnizing the ſame time conſtantly with publike aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, adminiſtration of the Sacrament, and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the poore, doth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently teſtifie, that they were not ignorant of the day, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> had conſecrated. <hi>At Troas they came together, the firſt day of the weeke, to</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Act. 20. 7.</note> 
                        <hi>breake bread:</hi> that is, to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the <hi>LORDS-ſupper</hi> and then and there <hi>Paul</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:16033:70"/> vnto them till midnight. The <hi>Corinthians,</hi> vſing every firſt day of the weeke to come together, were directed by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> by way of almes, as GOD had bleſſed them, to lay aſide ſomewhat for the poore Saints. And the ſame precept had he alſo giuen to the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Galatia:</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of S. <hi>Ierome</hi> thus writeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilantius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>On the firſt day of the weeke, (that is, on the LORDS-day</hi>) Paul <hi>commanded that all ſhould beſtow that, which ſhould be caried for reliefe to Ieruſalem</hi> The like order was kept in the ages following, by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and in all places, ever ſince there hath beene the obſervation of that day, whereſoeuer the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath beene embraced.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:16033:70"/>
                  <head>Obiection. 2.</head>
                  <p>The Apoſtle ſharply taxeth the <hi>Galatians,</hi> for preferring one time before another, ſaying. Yee obſerue dayes, and moneths, and yeeres: I am in feare of you, leſt I have beſtowed on you Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vaine. <hi>Gal. 4. 10.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is moſt competent for the explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his owne meaning: which being rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, yeeldeth no advantage to them, that vrge it; nor any way diminiſheth the eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and account, which the <hi>LORDS-day,</hi> by right, ought of all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to be had in. For, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> he declareth what thoſe dayes were, which were kept
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:16033:71"/> with ſuch offenſe, and danger;<note place="margin">Col. 2. 16. 17.</note> namely, the <hi>Legall Holy-daies</hi> and new moones and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-dayes, <hi>being but ſhadowes of things to come.</hi> Whereas that, which we celebrate, is for the ioyfull, and thankfull memoriall of the perfect ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of worke of <hi>Redemption,</hi> by them prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection 3.</head>
                  <p>The whole life of a Chriſtian is a continuall Sabbath, in reſting from ſinne; as the Apoſtle ſaith. He, that is entred into his reſt, hath ceaſed from his own worke as GOD did from his; <hi>Heb. 4. 10.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>It is doubtfull what theſe Obiectors intend, by the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:16033:71"/> terme of <hi>Sabbath:</hi> Whether they would haue it properly taken, ſo as it is the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Or by way of reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, as onely alluding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought to be holy all the dayes of their life, and abſtaine from ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, as the Iewes were inioyned to ſanctifie the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day</hi> in a ſpeciall maner, and to forbeare all labor, and travell. Let it be vnderſtood of whether they pleaſe, and it will ſtand them in little ſtead for this purpoſe. If they meane it in the former ſenſe, they muſt needs make a ſtrange al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, in the ſtate of GODS Commandements, to bring the obedience due to them all within the compaſſe of one, and ſo make it a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent, as though the doing of every duty of religion, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:16033:72"/> righteouſneſſe; and the ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of every vice of impiety, impuritie, and iniquity, were the keeping of that one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement; and ſo loue to GOD, and Man ſhould be incloſed in a narrower roome, then formerly it hath beene. <hi>GOD is not the author of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 33.</note> as by this he ſhould be made; if they plead alowance from him, for their vncouth <hi>Paradoxe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Shall we thinke, that at the Law-giuing, he minded this, by ſaying; (<hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour) Thou oughteſt to Remember the Sabbath day, to keepe it holy?</hi> Or, when he ſaid; <hi>In it thou ſhalt doe no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worke:</hi> that is, <hi>Thou ſhalt make no graven image:</hi> or, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery?</hi> Did the <hi>LORD,</hi> in the <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Prophets,</hi> any where ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:16033:72"/> himſelfe?</p>
                     <p>Or did <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the <hi>Law,</hi> put any ſuch new meaning into it? And in confounding the ſanctifying of the <hi>Sabbath-day,</hi> with holy behaviour <hi>eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-day;</hi> one of two extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will hardly, with any poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility be avoyded: That ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no ordinary worke may be done at any time, but <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> muſt live alwaies as the <hi>Iſralites</hi> were Commanded to doe, on the Seuenth-day. Or elſe that no certaine ſeaſon is to be exempted from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon affaires, and ſet apart for the worſhip and ſeruice of GOD, in publike aſſemblies more then all others.</p>
                     <p>Neither haue ſervants, and ſuch as are vnder the yoke, any time of reſt &amp; refreſhing aſſigned vnto them, by divine ordinance. Now the former
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:16033:73"/> of theſe is palpable, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſuperſtition: and the latter intollerable, and cruell prophaneſſe. Now, if they will ſay, that their words are ſtretched beyond their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, (they onely propoſing the <hi>Sabbath-day</hi> for a modell and rule of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> mens liues; that they ſhould not onely for the ſeuenth part thereof declare their piety, and devotion; but in all the reſt demeane themſelues in an holy maner:) we reply, that their pretence, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting againſt vs this perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sabbath is wholy imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and frivolous.</p>
                     <p>For vpon that ground, the <hi>Fourth Commandement</hi> might haue beene ſpared altogether, as neuer needing to be either ſpoken, or written; ſithence <hi>Iſraell</hi> was an holy people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, before there were any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:16033:73"/> 
                        <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned them, in caſe they would be <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> that they<note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>Should keepe iudgement, and doe righteouſnes at altimes.</hi> And yet they were bound to Sanctifie the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that <hi>Seuenth-day</hi> that the LORD Commended vnto them, without which they could not haue bin holy: as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> cannot now be any day, that ſhall contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, or careleſly neglect the <hi>LORDS-day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In regard of their holineſſe they are by GOD himſelfe,<note place="margin">Exod. 19. 6.</note> called by the name of <hi>Prieſts, a Kingdom of Prieſts, Prieſts vnto him,</hi> or his <hi>Prieſts.</hi> And yet <hi>Aarons Prieſt-hood,</hi> and that of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Levi</hi> was not diſſolved, by this alluſion to their function, and ſervice.</p>
                     <p>We <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> are titled by the name of <hi>Kings:</hi> and ſhal there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:16033:74"/> no ſubiection be yeelded to the Princes, and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, who are ſet over vs, in authority, and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Beſide this, many have not yet attained vnto any ſound ſanctification: they muſt be brought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, by the helpe of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, on the <hi>LORDS-day.</hi> And ſome are ſoundly ſanctified, but not greatly. And ſome are ſanctified greatly, but none perfectly. This Sabbath, with the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the holy ordinances therein, is as needfull, and commodious to all theſe, as watring, or raine is, for the rooting, groweth, and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of plants, in gardens and orchards.</p>
                     <p>As for the <hi>Reſt,</hi> ſpoken of in the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> by them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. It is not the preſent Condition of any mortall
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:16033:74"/> Creature, in this world, but that eternall felicity in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whereunto faith leadeth the beleevers, and giueth them as certaine aſſurance of, as if they were now preſently put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their foot into it: and there is a ceſſation indeed, not onely from ſinne, but from all maner calamities; as the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> informed <hi>John</hi> in his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13</note> And thereout the hard-hearted, and vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Iſralites</hi> were excluded, according to the oath, which GOD ſware in his wrath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on due cauſe kindled againſt<note place="margin">Iun. Paral. in Heb. 4. 5.</note> them. And <hi>Learned Iunius</hi> his iudgement is, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> is he principally, that in the behalfe of his Church, aſwell as for himſelfe, hath entred into the poſſeſsion of that <hi>Reſt,</hi> firſt ſpoken of by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and then by <hi>David,</hi> and here more largely diſcourſed of,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:16033:75"/> and amplified by this <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> For ſo, by a kind of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe, he maketh plaine, and perſpicuouſly vnfoldeth the ſenſe of this place.</p>
                     <list type="syllogism">
                        <item>
                           <hi>Whither the head of the Church, and Prince of GODS people is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, thither ſhall the Church, and people of GOD likewiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>But he is entred into his Reſt, and gloriouſly ceaſeth from his works wherein he was exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, during the time of his humiliation, whiles he was in the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:16033:75"/> forme of a ſervant; as GOD once reſted from the works of his Creation, after they were accompliſhed.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thither therefore ſhall the People of GOD enter and the body ſhall be vnited to the head, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>This interpretation hath in it very great probability of the true meaning of the Text, eſpecially ſeeing there is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place alſo, in the ſame <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> in ſome ſorte agreeing with it; as where it is ſaid, that the <hi>Hope, which is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, we haue as an ancre of the ſoule, both ſure, and ſtedfaſt, and it entreth into that, which is within the vaile; whither the fore runner is for us entred in, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:16033:76"/>
                     <p>And here may be diſcerned a fit proportion betweene the worke of the <hi>Creator,</hi> and the worke of the <hi>Redeemer:</hi> And betweene the <hi>Reſting</hi> of the <hi>Creator,</hi> and the <hi>Reſting</hi> of the <hi>Redeemer.</hi> And where as it is ſaid to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> that the <hi>Holy-dayes, and New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moones, and Sabbaths were a ſhadow of things to come. But the Body is in Chriſt.</hi> We may vnderſtand by this how the <hi>Types,</hi> and the <hi>thing repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them</hi> accord together. His heavenly <hi>Reſt</hi> for vs was liuely thereby prefigured; and that being obtained, their terme is expired, and come to a period.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection 4.</head>
                  <p>The iudgement of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and of ſundry Fathers are againſt the obſervation of any</p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:16033:76"/>
                  <p>Sabbath, eſpecially of the LORD S-day, more then of any other time. For they would haue the Sabbath to be ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally kept continually.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TERTVLLIAN</hi> againſt the Iewes.</p>
                  <p>We keepe the Sabbath, not every Seventh-day: but every day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHRYSOSTOM</hi> in a Sermon againſt the New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moones.</p>
                  <p>A Chriſtian ought not to celebrate Moneths, or New-moons, or LORDS dayes: But to keepe a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Holy-day, during his life.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:16033:77"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AVGVSTINE</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Quiſquis illum diem obſervat, vt litera ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>at, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliter ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Spir. et Lit. cap. 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer keepeth the day, as the Letter foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſavoureth of the fleſh.</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The names of theſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ancients are brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the keeping of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; and ſo are their words: but not their iudgements, and meaning. For we may eaſily gather, that ſome of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued ſuch, as made ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of holineſſe on the <hi>LORDS-day,</hi> and liued li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenciouſly at all other times: and therefore oppoſeth vnto them the contrary practize of ſound, and true-hearted <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:16033:77"/>
                     <p>Some of them dealt againſt the <hi>Sabbatarians,</hi> and ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Iewiſhly obſerued ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brogated <hi>Seuenth day.</hi> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall keepe [That Day) ſavoureth of the fleſh.</hi> But not<note place="margin">Illum Diem</note> whoſoeuer obſerveth any day, For his owne words teſtifie the contrary; which are theſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The LORDS-day the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Serm de tempo 251.</note> 
                        <hi>Apoſtles, and Apoſtolicall men, haue ordained with religious holineſſe to bee kept; becauſe in the ſame, our Redeemer roſe from the dead, &amp; therfore is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the Do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>inical or Lords-day: that in it, wee may onely attend on the Divine
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:16033:78"/> ſervice. This is the firſt day of the world: in it were created the Ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, and the Angels: vpon this day Chriſt roſe, and the Holy-Ghoſt was given, and Manna de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended firſt from heaven, vpon this day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And in another place;</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>As Mary the Mother of our LORD is the chiefe among women. So among other daies, this is the mother of the reſt. The whole grace of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and the ancient feſtivitie of the people of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:16033:78"/> the Iewes, is changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſolemnitie of this day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In both theſe ſayings, who doth not ſee that Saint <hi>Augn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> is much wronged by them, that peruert and ſtraine his writings to ſo bitter a cenſure of them, that ſanctifie the LORDS-Day, as to <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the fleſh,</hi> and ſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre deſtruction, as Mr. <hi>Broad</hi> inforceth the matter, <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. 8.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>Auſtine</hi> of the old Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is not ſingular, and the onely man that ſpeaketh in the commendation of the LORDS-Day: but many other both before him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him haue been of the ſame mind with him, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their workes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Athanaſius</hi> intreating of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In Mat</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 11.</note> theſe words of our Sauiour
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:16033:79"/> Chriſt, (<hi>All things are giuen me of my Father,</hi>) ſaith</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>As long as the old World did laſt, ſo long continued the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sabbath: But, when another generation did ſucceed, it was not needfull that this new peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould any longer keep the day of the former Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but rather the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſecond creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Age: and when is that beginning, but at the time, when our LORD did riſe againe?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> among the ſundry names, which he recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:16033:79"/> vp, that this day had, in the Primitiue Church, ſaith,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It was therefore called</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Serm. 5. de Reſur.</note> 
                        <hi>the LORDS-Day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was ſolemnly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the memory of Chriſt his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Juſtine Martyr,</hi> ſpeaking of the day which Chriſtians kept in his time, which is the LORDS-Day, that we now keep, giueth this reaſon of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Becauſe vpon that</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Apog. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Day Chriſt did riſe from the dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>ORIGEN ſaith; <hi>Vpon</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hom. 7. in Exod.</note> 
                        <hi>the</hi> LORDS-Day, <hi>the</hi> LORD <hi>alwaies raineth Manna from Heauen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:16033:80"/>
                     <p>HIEROME ſaith; <hi>Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ad Euſtich.</note> 
                        <hi>the</hi> LORDS-Day, <hi>they giue themſelues one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Prayer and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And AMBROSE ſaith;<note place="margin">Serm. 33.</note> 
                        <hi>Let all the Day bee ſpent in Prayer and Reading: let no Secular Acts hinder Diuine Acts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By theſe Teſtimonies, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled out from many others that might bee alleadged, it may appeare which way the current and ſtreame of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> was wont to runne: That the Day which we keepe was deriued from the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and Primitiue Church, to thoſe ages; and from them to all that haue followed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till theſe our dayes, wherein
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:16033:80"/> it hath found the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obiection. 5.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſtian people choſe the firſt day, and made it their Sabbath; ſaith the Booke of Homilies. By the Doctrine then</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Broad. Pag. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>of our Church, the obſeruation of the LORDS-Day, is an Eccleſiaſticall Ordinance, and not an Apoſtolicall Precept.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Sundry attempts haue been hitherto made, to impaire &amp; diminiſh the eſtimation and account, which the LORDS-Day formerly hath beene, &amp; ſtill ought to be had in, of all GODS people: Some from pretence of Scripture; ſome from ſhew of Reaſon; Some from the opinions of learned
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:16033:81"/> men; and now the Doctrine of our owne Church is vrged, that which is by publike au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority eſtabliſhed, (as wee confeſſe the <hi>Homilies</hi> are) as though this Sabbath could not be iuſtified to be of Diuine In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitution, without derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from our Church and ſtate: But let the <hi>Homily</hi> bee duely peruſed, and well conſidered of, and it will more ſtrongly confirme, then diſharten vs, from the defenſe of it. Is this good reaſoning. <hi>Chriſtian People choſe the day: Therefore</hi> GOD <hi>did not appoint it?</hi> Why? GOD appointed <hi>Dauid</hi> to bee King ouer <hi>Iſraell;</hi> and yet the people choſe him. And<note place="margin">1 Chron. 29. 22.</note> 
                        <hi>Salomon</hi> was ſet vp by the LORD; and yet the people declared their choyce by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him King the ſecond time, and annointing of him.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 24. 22</note> 
                        <hi>Ioſhua</hi> called the people to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:16033:81"/> witneſſe, <hi>That they had choſen the LORD to ſerue him:</hi> and yet the Lord firſt offered himſelfe vnto them. <hi>Mary</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 10. 42.</note> 
                        <hi>choſe the good part,</hi> but it was that holy Doctrine, which Chriſt deliuered to her, and no inuention of her owne head.</p>
                     <p>Their chooſing then may well bee taken for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of that fit time, which GOD, by his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> then had aſsigned vnto them, for their meetings, to doe him ſeruice, and the relinquiſhing of the Idolatrous times, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were wont to aſſemble for the worſhipping of the Heathen Gods. And it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry likely, that the Antiquated Sabbath was tendred vnto them, with the other legall rites, by thoſe of the ſect of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> by whom many Churches were grieuouſly
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:16033:82"/> troubled; whereof thoſe in <hi>Galatia</hi> may ſerue for a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> But the beſt way to ſhew, how theſe words are heere wreſted, is to recite the whole Diſcourſe, both in the ſentence going before, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in thoſe, that follow after; and that will clearely declare the ſacred authority of our Sabbath, and the Orthodoxall iudgement of our Church; in the acknowledgement of the ſame. Theſe are the words thereof.<note place="margin">Homil. Of the time and place of Prayer. Part. 1. Pag. 124. 125.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Concerning the time which Almighty GOD hath appointed his people to aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſolemnly, it doth appeare by the Fourth Commandement of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:16033:82"/> GOD: <hi>Remember,</hi> (ſaith GOD) <hi>that thou keepe holy the Sabbath-Day.</hi> Vpon which day, (as it is plaine in the Acts of the Apoſtles)<note place="margin">Act. 13.</note> the people accuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reſorted together, and heard diligently the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets read among them. And albeit this Law doth not ſo ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bind Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to obſerue the vtter Ceremonies thereof, as it was giuen to the Iewes, touching the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:16033:83"/> forbearing worke and labour on that day, in the time of great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity; and as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preciſe keeping the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uenth-Day, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of the Iewes, (for wee keepe their Firſt-Day now, which is our Sunday and make that our Sabbath, which is our day of reſt, in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> who vpon that day roſe from the dead, conquering it moſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphantly.) Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:16033:83"/> was found in the Commandement ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the Law of nature, as a thing moſt godly, moſt iuſt, and needfull for the ſetting forth of GODS glory; it ought to bee reteined, and kept of all Chriſtian people. And therefore, by this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, we ought to haue a time, as one day in a Weeke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee ought to reſt, yea, from our neceſſary and needfull labour: for like as it appeareth by this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:16033:84"/> wee ought not to bee ſlothfull or idle, but diligently to labour in that ſtate wherein GOD hath ſet vs: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo GOD hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen expreſſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, that vpon the Sabbath day, which is now our Sunday) wee ſhould ceaſe from all workeday and Week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Workeday and week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labour to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.</note> labour: Euen ſo GODS obedient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould vſe the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day holily, &amp; reſt from their common and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſſe; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:16033:84"/> to giue themſelues wholly to heauenly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of GODS true Religion and Seruice. So that GOD doth not onely command the obſeruation of this holy-day: but alſo by his own example doth ſtirre vs vp to the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent keeping of the ſame. Good naturall Children will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become obedient to the Commandement of their Parents; but alſo haue a diligent eye to their doings, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:16033:85"/> gladly follow the ſame. So, if wee will bee the Children of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, wee muſt bee carefull to keepe the Chriſtian Sabbath day, which is the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day: Not onely that it is GODS expreſſe Commandement: but that wee may declare our ſelues to be louing Children, in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the example of our gracious LORD, &amp; Father. This plainely it may appeare, that GODS will &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:16033:85"/> is, to haue a ſolemne time and ſtanding Day in the Weeke, wherein the people ſhould come together, and haue in remembrance his holy Acts and wonderfull benefits and to render him thankes for them, as appertaineth to lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, kinde, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent people. This exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; commandement of GOD, the holy Chriſtian people began to follow immediately after the aſcenſion of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:16033:86"/> Chriſt, and began to chooſe them a ſtanding Day in the Weeke, to come together in. Yet not the Seuenth day which the Iſraelites kept, but the LORDS day, the day of the<note place="margin">Scriptures alleadged to warrant the Lords Day.</note> LORDS Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the day after the Seuenth day, the firſt day of the Weeke; whereof there is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by St. <hi>Paul</hi> made on this wiſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In the firſt day of the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.</note> 
                        <hi>Weeke, let euery man lay vp what hee thinketh
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:16033:86"/> good,</hi> (meaning for the poore.) By the firſt day of the Weeke is meant our Sunday, which is the firſt day after the Iewes ſeuenth day. And in the Apocalyps it is<note place="margin">Apoc 1.</note> more plaine; where S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith; <hi>Hee was in the Spirit vpon the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</hi> Since which time GODS people haue alwayes in all Ages, without any gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vſed to come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the Sunday, to celebrate &amp; honour the LORDS bleſſed
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:16033:87"/> name, and carefully to keepe that day in holy reſt &amp; quietneſſe, both<note place="margin">Holy reſt.</note> men and women, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſeruants and ſtrangers. For the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion and breach of which day, GOD hath declared himſelfe much to be grieued; as it may appeare by him, who, for gathering ſtickes on the Sabbath<note place="margin">Numb. 15.</note> day, was ſtoned to death. But (alas;) all theſe notwithſtanding, it is lamentable to ſee the wicked boldneſſe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:16033:87"/> of thoſe who would be accounted GODS children; yet paſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all for the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and hallowing the Sunday. And theſe people are of two ſorts: the one ſort, if they haue ought to doe, though there bee no extreame neceſsity of doing it, yet they muſt not ſpare for the Sunday; they muſt ride and iourney on the Sunday; they muſt driue and carry on the Sunday; they muſt row
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:16033:88"/> and ferry on the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; they muſt buy and ſell on the Sunday; they muſt keepe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets and Faires on the Sunday; finally, they keepe all dayes alike; holy-dayes and worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies are all one. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort are yet worſe: for, though they will not trauel or labour on the Sunday, as they doe on the Weeke-day; yet will they not reſt in holineſſe, as GOD commandeth: but they reſt in vngodlineſſe &amp;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:16033:88"/> filthineſſe; preſuming in their pride, pranking and pricking, pointing and painting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to bee gorgeous and gay: they reſt in exceſſe, and ſuperfluity in gluttony and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, like Rats and Swine; they reſt in brawling and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, in rayling, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling and fighting; they reſt in wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, toyiſh talking, and filthineſſe; ſo that it doth appeare too e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently, the LORD
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:16033:89"/> is more diſhonoured, the Diuell better ſerued on that day then on all the dayes of the weeke beſides.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>ANd now for a ſummary Recapitulation of the maine heads and points in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of: <hi>If all the morall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts be perpetuall: If the fourth Commandement bee a morall Precept: If all conſecrated time bee the obſeruation of the fourth Commandement, during the time of the Conſecration of it: And, If the LORDS-Day, by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of GODS Word,</hi> and of learned Writers, both mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:16033:89"/> and ancient, and of the Doctrine of this our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Engliſh Church, or nation: Then let them that be aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to it, remember them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues timely, and ceaſe to contend againſt the Law, and Ordinance of the LORD. The truth of the cauſe is bright and ſhining, and very cleare to thoſe that ſeriouſly deſire to bee informed in it; howeuer it dazle the eyes of ſuch as reſolue with wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to perſiſt in their owne opinions. They may (no doubt) and daily doe, draw others to their part; but ſo they doe alſo to their perill. It is an vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſſe to proſper in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting of mens ſoules, and making a ſide againſt their Maker: For they muſt thinke and know, that the bloud of the ſeduced, will in time bee required at their hands. And
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:16033:90"/> on the contrary ſide, they are all in comfortable and bleſſed eſtate, who (together with faith in the Goſpell, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of other duties of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe) do in the faithfulneſſe of their hearts, and wayes, ſanctifie this day in obedience to the Commandement of GOD their <hi>Creator,</hi> and for a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full memoriall of the work of Saluation finiſhed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> their <hi>Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16033:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
